<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2014 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This printing plugin provides a simple yet compelling example of how
  platform independent web map printing might be implemented. Our
  implementation bypasses the browsers native printing functionality by
  rendering server side to a PDF document, which is then automatically
  downloaded to the browser. The PDF document can either be saved to the file
  system or opened in a new browser window from which native PDF printing is
  possible. As different browsers are allowed to - and will - render identical
  HTML pages in a slightly different manner, an absolute format like PDF is a
  necessity for creating reproducible prints.</para>

  <para>Our implementation makes extensive use of the excellent iText
  library<footnote>
      <para>"iText is a library that allows you to generate PDF files on the
      fly", see http://itextpdf.com/</para>
    </footnote>, which allows direct drawing operations on a graphics context.
  This has the advantage of preserving the vectorial nature of the features in
  a layer, allowing crisp vector rendering at any zoom level.</para>

  <section id="backend">
    <title>Back-end</title>

    <para>The printing plugin consists of a client part (the client GWT) that
    is responsible for the user interaction and a back-end part that is
    responsible for the generation of the PDF document. To achieve sufficient
    flexibility in the layout and composition of the PDF document, the
    document is conceptually a tree of nested components, each of which is
    responsible for its own rendering.</para>

    <para>The following set of components have been implemented:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>PageComponent</emphasis>: a container component for
        the complete PDF page.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>MapComponent</emphasis>: this represents the main map.
        The layers, scale bar, legend and other components are child members
        of the map.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>LabelComponent</emphasis>: can be used for an
        arbitrary text label, e.g. a title.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>ImageComponent</emphasis>: represents an arbitrary
        static image, e.g. a north arrow on a map.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>VectorlayerComponent</emphasis>: draws a vector layer
        on the map.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>RasterLayerComponent</emphasis>: draws a raster layer
        on the map.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>ScaleBarComponent</emphasis>: draws a scale bar on the
        map.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>LegendComponent</emphasis>: draws a legend on the
        map.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>ViewPortComponent</emphasis>: a view port is a smaller
        map that is an inset of the main map and is used to highlight details
        of the main map.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>Print components</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/components.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The layout is determined by recursively calculating the preferred
    size of each component first (which can vary according to font sizes,
    margins, etc...) followed by a second pass in which the layout constraints
    of each component are used to align the component with respect to its
    parent. This approach is top-down, starting with the root PageComponent.
    The following layout constraints are possible:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>width</emphasis>: the preferred width of the
        component.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>height</emphasis>: the preferred height of the
        component.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>marginX</emphasis>: the margin in the x-direction or
        the x-position in case of absolute alignment in the
        x-direction.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>marginY</emphasis>: the margin in the y-direction or
        the y-position in case of absolute alignment in the
        y-direction.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>alignmentX</emphasis>: the alignment type in the
        x-direction (left, right, justified or absolute).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>alignmentY</emphasis>: the alignment type in the
        y-direction (left, right, justified or absolute).</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
