<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2014 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<chapter id="chapter-configuration">
  <title>Configuration</title>

  <para>This chapter will describe the procedure to configure the Geomajas web
  application and modify the jmeter installation to allow Geomajas performance
  testing.</para>

  <section id="dependencies">
    <title>Web application dependencies</title>

    <para>To allow for jmeter testing, you must add the following dependency
    to your web application.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Plug-in dependency</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.plugin&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-plugin-jmeter&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Once the dependency is correctly included, everything is set up
    automatically. In the startup logs, you should see an extra URL mapping
    appearing:</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>JMeter configuration</title>

    <para>Start by installing JMeter. The recommended version of Apache JMeter
    (TM) is 2.11 (we have not tested other versions). See <ulink
    url="https://jmeter.apache.org">https://jmeter.apache.org</ulink> for
    installation instructions, which boil down to unzipping the tar ball in a
    directory of your choice (we will refer to this directory as<code>
    JMETER_HOME</code>). </para>

    <para>After the installation is done, you should add the Geomajas jmeter
    client jar to your installation. Copy the following maven artifact to the
    directory <code>JMETER_HOME/lib/ext</code>:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.plugin&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-plugin-jmeter-client&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>This artifact can be downloaded from the <ulink
    url="http://repo.geomajas.org/nexus/index.html">Geomajas nexus
    server</ulink> or the public maven repository (for releases). The jar is
    an "überjar" that contains all the dependencies and is made using the
    maven Shade plugin.</para>

    <para>After starting up jmeter, the following GUI should appear:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Jmeter startup screen</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/jmeter-startup.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Add a thread group to your test plan and a Java request:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Jmeter java request in thread group</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/jmeter-java-request.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Select the GeomajasSamplerClient as classname:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Jmeter Geomajas sampler client</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/jmeter-geomajas.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>You can now configure the following request parameters:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>baseUrl: the base URL for accessing your Geomajas server. This
        URL is typically constructed by adding the extension
        <code>/d/performance</code> to the URL of your Geomajas web
        context.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>appId: the Geomajas application id (see the Spring
        context)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>mapId: the Geomajas map id (see the Spring context)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>layerIds: (optional) a comma-separated list of layer ids (client
        layer ids, see the Geomajas Spring context)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>runMode: random (for randomly selecting tiles for all allowed
        layers) or topdown (for creating a pyramid by iterating scale levels
        top down)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>tileCount: the total number of tiles to be fetched</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>saveTiles: whether the tiles should be saved to the file
        system</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>username: username for basic authentication</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>password: password for basic authentication</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>userToken: user token for accessing the Geomajas server (if the
        server is secured). The token can be picked from a tile request (using
        firebug, request parameter= userToken) after accessing your server via
        the browser or sniffed from server logging. As the authentication
        method may differ, we have not made this part of the jmeter
        plugin.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>tileFolder: absolute path to a folder were the tiles can be
        stored</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The logging GUI can be activated by selecting options-&gt;Log
    Viewer. It is also available from JMETER_HOME/bin/jmeter.log. The logging
    will show you all the available client layers, which can be handy:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Logging activated</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/jmeter-logging.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>
