<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2016 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The caching plug-in allows you to speed-up the performance of the
  Geomajas system. By deep integration into the functioning of the system,
  this can be done in a way which prevents stale data from being presented to
  the user.</para>

  <para>Thanks to the use of pipelines when rendering tiles and doing updates
  of data, and thanks to the power of the configuration system, Geomajas is
  very flexible with regards to choices of when and how to apply
  caching.</para>

  <para>The system is sufficiently powerful to provide many use cases,
  including<itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>keeping data cached for a pre-configured period</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>limiting the size of the cache according to a strategy</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>evicting cached data to disk according to a strategy to reduce
        cache memory consumption</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>invalidation of cached data when it overlaps with a certain
        area, avoiding stale data</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>smart invalidation based on an area, only invalidating when
        objects where the cache may be visible (based on zoom level)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>clustered cache</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>...</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para></para>

  <section id="overview">
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>The caching is enabled by adding steps and interceptors to the
    default pipelines at some of the hooks. Two of the example pipelines are
    the GetVectorTile and SaveOrUpdate pipelines.</para>

    <para>The GetVectorTile pipeline can be enhanced to support caching as in
    figure <xref linkend="fig-getvectortile-pipeline" />. Interceptors are
    added to get items from the cache and or store them in the cache. This is
    specifically the cache for caching the entire tile and for getting the
    features (strictly speaking feature caching is done in the get features
    pipeline).</para>

    <figure id="fig-getvectortile-pipeline">
      <title>Cache interceptors in the GetVectorTile pipeline</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/GetTileCacheHooks.png" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>This is a pipeline only reads data and thus only shows how to get
    data from the cache. In figure <xref
    linkend="fig-saveorupdate-pipeline" /> below a part of the SaveOrUpdate
    pipeline is shown. As all changes to data occur through this layer, it is
    useful to handle invalidation of cached data.</para>

    <figure id="fig-saveorupdate-pipeline">
      <title>Cache hooks in (a part of) the SaveOrUpdate pipeline</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/SaveOrUpdateCacheHooks.png" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>For each category of objects, a different cache configuration can be
    used. Each combination of layer and category can use a different cache
    implementation. The type of spatial index can also be chosen per layer and
    category combination. This is all managed by the
    CacheManagerService.</para>

    <figure id="fig-cache-layer-category">
      <title>CacheManager and cache per layer and category</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/caches-type-layer.png" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Each cache or index implementation has it's own configuration which
    may again depend on the layer and category.</para>

    <para>The different caches for a layer work together as shown in figure
    <xref linkend="figure-cache-usage-raster" />. This displays the handling
    of a request for a raster image, for example the image for a rasterized
    tile. The request handler first check whether the image is available in
    the cache. If this is the case, the image is returned to the client. If
    not, the rebuild cache is used to convert the image name into a the
    context which is used to (re)start the pipeline to build the raster image.
    During the execution of the pipeline, the feature cache may be used to
    avoid queries on the data source for the image.</para>

    <figure id="figure-cache-usage-raster">
      <title>Handling a request for the image part of a rasterized
      tile</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/rasterization-cache.png" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The reason for the use of different caches is the configuration of
    the cache.</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The raster cache does not need to store much in memory. The
          data may very quickly be evicted to disk. On disk this cache may be
          allowed to grow very big (disk space is cheaper than memory). It can
          be chosen how long data is kept. Removing data from the cache is no
          problem as the image can be rendered at any time. Keeping data in
          memory is no real advantage as the only purpose is to stream the
          data to the network.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The rebuild cache contains many small objects to allow
          rebuilding of rendered tiles. The data should not be removed for a
          reasonably long amount of time (the maximum duration of a session)
          as the tiles would otherwise be impossible to rebuild. Evicting to
          disk is no problem, the time required to read the pipeline context
          from disk is likely to be small compared to the evaluation of the
          pipeline.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The feature cache is used to cache data store queries.
          Evicting to disk is less useful as the original query could also be
          repeated.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section id="security">
    <title>Security</title>

    <para>The cache also has to consider security. All entries in the cache
    are stored based on keys. These keys are determined based on the context
    which is relevant when building the cached object, including the security
    context. When a key is determined, as the key is determined using a
    hashing algorithm, the chances of having two different contexts which may
    to the same key is very small. Still, when putting an object in the cache,
    if the key was already used in the cache, it is checked that the cache
    context (including security) matches and if not, the key is modified to
    make it unique.</para>

    <para>The situation as displayed in figure <xref
    linkend="figure-cache-usage-raster" /> is a little bit different. When
    requesting (cached) images to be served, they key is used as (part of) the
    URL. The default behaviour in this case is that the security token is not
    included in the URL and this the matching of the security context can not
    be done. This is explicitly done to be able to serve the images faster.
    However, the URL can be considered secret as they cannot be predicted. As
    such you will normally see the tile as it was previously calculated.
    However, it is possible that the rights for a user changes which would
    result in changed data. It is possible that the cache represents
    information according to old rights. There are two possible solutions, one
    is to explicitly invalidate the caches when rights are changed. The other
    is to limit the life of cache entries (notably including the rebuild
    cache).</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
