<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-configuration">
  <title>Configuration</title>

  <para>The configuration of the REST plugin consists of a maven part and a
  web MVC part.</para>

  <section id="dependencies">
    <title>Dependencies</title>

    <para>Make sure your include the plug-in in your project. If you are using
    Maven, add the following dependency to your pom:</para>

    <example>
      <title>Plug-in dependency</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
  &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas&lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-face-rest&lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;1.0&lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section id="WebMVC">
    <title>Web MVC configuration</title>

    <para>The web configuration is by default based on the bean name URL
    handler mapping. This means that the name of the scanned controller beans
    determines the URL base that points to the REST services. More
    specifically, the RestController class (see below) has an annotation that
    tells the DispatcherServlet to map all urls that start with<code>
    http://{host}:{port}/{context}/{dispatcher}/rest/ </code>to the REST
    service, where <code>host</code>, <code>port</code> and
    <code>context</code> should be replaced with the host, port and web
    context of your deployment and <code>/{dispatcher}/*</code> is the url
    pattern of the DispatcherServlet mapping (as configured in
    web.xml).</para>

    <warning>
      <para>the current faces depend on the mapping of <code>/d/*</code> to
      the DispatcherServlet !</para>
    </warning>

    <programlisting>@Controller("/rest/**")
public class RestController {
   @RequestMapping(value = "/rest/{layerId}/{featureId}.json", method = RequestMethod.GET){
...
}</programlisting>

    <para>Further narrowing of the url mapping to class methods is done
    through the <code>RequestMapping</code> annotations. For a thorough
    explanation of the various url parameters we refer to the next chapter,
    which explains the usage of the REST face as a client. Unless you
    absolutely want to change the url path, there is no need to override the
    default configuration. If you do want to change this, however, one
    possibility is to add additional mappings by configuring a
    SimpleUrlHandlerMapping bean, which allows mapping of arbitrary paths to
    controller beans.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
