<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2011 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-dojo-configuration">
  <title>dojo Configuration</title>

  <para>For the dojo face to function properly, it is important that your
  web.xml contains the references to the necessary information and servlets.
  Let's dissect an example web.xml file.</para>

  <para>The file starts with the reference and configuration of the Geomajas
  context listener. This assures the application configuration is available
  for Geomajas and indicates the location of the additional configuration
  files. The configuration files are always searched on the classpath. You may
  include the "classpath:" or "classpath*:" prefix if you want (recommended to
  allow your IDE to check existence of the resources).</para>

  <xi:include href="listing/WebXmlDojoPart1.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <para>Next up is the definition of the actual servlets which are needed. The
  order in which they need to be initialised is also specified.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><code>JsonServlet</code>: the servlet which allows you to execute
      commands by sending the request as JSON and which returns the result as
      JSON as well.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para><code>DispatcherServlet</code>: this is primarily used to deliver
      the Geomajas and dojo script files and resources, assuring that they are
      properly cached and gzip compressed. It can also be used by plug-ins to
      additional services, for example for delivering PDF files by a printing
      plug-in.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <xi:include href="listing/WebXmlDojoPart2.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <para>To finish, the servlet mappings need to be defined. You don't really
  have a lot of choice here, as the client side JavaScript expects these
  values.</para>

  <xi:include href="listing/WebXmlDojoPart3.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <para>To finish, the servlet mappings need to be defined. You don't really
  have a lot of choice here, as the client side JavaScript expects these
  values.</para>

  <para>In many cases you also want to do some client side configurations.
  This can be done in one of two ways.</para>

  <para>You can include a "geomajas-constants.js" file in your code (the name
  of the file can differ).</para>

  <xi:include href="listing/GeomajasConstantsJs.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <para>You can override some configurations in your html file, on the script
  tags in head.</para>

  <xi:include href="listing/HtmlIncludeConfig.xml"
              xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

  <section id="gmaps">
    <title>Using Google maps raster layer</title>

    <para>To use the Google maps raster layer in the dojo face, you have to
    include the Google maps API files in your application to allow Geomajas to
    use those. This can be done using code like the following</para>

    <example>
      <title>Google API inclusion</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;script type="text/javascript"
    src="http://maps.google.com/maps?file=api&amp;amp;v=2&amp;amp;sensor=false&amp;amp;key=ABCDEF"&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>or</para>

    <example>
      <title>Google API inclusion using Google loader</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;script type="text/javascript" src="http://www.google.com/jsapi?key=ABCDEFG"&gt;
&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;
    google.load("maps", "2.95");
&lt;/script&gt;</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>Note that you do need to have a Google maps key ("ABCDEF" is used in
    the example above) if you want to deploy your site (it should work without
    when running your tests on "localhost").</para>

    <para>In your layer, you can determine the kind of layer by setting the
    "satellite" property. When this is true, satellite images will be
    displayed. When this is false, the normal Google maps images are used
    (street map).</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
