<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2014 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The administration plugin adds the capability to dynamically maintain
  the Geomajas Spring application context. Prior to this plugin, the
  application context was loaded once and for all at startup and any changes
  to the context would necessarily involve a restart of the complete web
  application. While this is standard practice for Spring-configured systems,
  it prevents common GIS administrative tasks like:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>dynamically configuring layers: vector layers, raster layers,
      styling, attributes, caching, security, ...</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>dynamically configuring fysical datastores: geodatabases,
      shapefiles</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>or more specific Geomajas-related tasks like:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>dynamically configuring applications: maps, layers, tools,
      etc...</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>dynamically configuring services and commands</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>There are various technical roads that could be pursued to reach this
  goal, some of them involving a complete rehaul of the existing service
  infrastructure. For this plugin we have tried to follow the least intrusive,
  yet most generic option, which is to directly perform application context
  changes on a runtime system. Initial testing has shown that this is a viable
  road, although some limitations have to be taken into account:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Spring Dependency Injection, and more particularly autowiring,
      will need to be reapplied to reestablish bean dependencies within the
      context. This is not part of the standard bean definition registration
      mechanism, although it can be achieved partially by manually rewiring
      certain bean types.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Application context persistence is a separate issue that comes
      into play when the context becomes dynamic. It will be handled by a
      separate persistence service.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Concurrency issues may pop up as a consequence of dynamic
      configuration. As Geomajas is a stateless system, this should have
      limited consequences in most cases, although some glitches may appear
      during the configuration stage. The overall approach here should be to
      avoid locks by only sharing immutable objects. In the end it is up to
      the service implementors to ensure proper behavior after
      reconfiguration.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section>
    <title></title>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
