<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  ~ This file is part of Geomajas, a component framework for building
  ~ rich Internet applications (RIA) with sophisticated capabilities for the
  ~ display, analysis and management of geographic information.
  ~ It is a building block that allows developers to add maps
  ~ and other geographic data capabilities to their web applications.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2010 Geosparc, http://www.geosparc.com, Belgium
  ~
  ~ This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
  ~ it under the terms of the GNU Affero General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the
  ~ License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  ~ MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
  ~ GNU Affero General Public License for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Affero General Public License
  ~ along with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
  -->
<chapter id="release" lang="en">
  <title>How to release Geomajas</title>

  <para>The Geomajas project consists of many pieces which each have their own
  release cycle. The most important parts are the back-end, faces and
  plug-ins. The example programs, documentation and and build tools also have
  individual release cycles.</para>

  <para>This chapter tries to explain how to release any of these modules. The
  procedure is similar for all modules, but there are some specific checks to
  be done which only apply for certain parts.</para>

  <para>As the releases are done to the Sonatype's nexus repository for open
  source projects (which is synced to Maven Central), the following references
  are a required read:</para>

  <para><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="https://docs.sonatype.org/display/Repository/Sonatype+OSS+Maven+Repository+Usage+Guide">Sonatype
        OSS Maven Repository Usage Guide</ulink></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><ulink
        url="http://www.sonatype.com/people/2010/01/how-to-generate-pgp-signatures-with-maven/">How
        to Generate PGP Signatures with Maven</ulink></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <para>The basic procedure is very easy, for the part you want to release,
  execute the following two commands (using the next version as parameter,
  this will make you type less). These steps should be done in a clean
  location, it is best to do a fresh checkout.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>mvn -DdevelopmentVersion=1.8.0-SNAPSHOT release:prepare</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>mvn release:perform</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Before doing the release, you should update the version which is
  mentioned in the master.xml file (this version is displayed on the front
  page of the manual and is not automatically updated). After the release,
  this should be updated to the new development version.</para>

  <para>At the end of the build, the src/main/resources/api.txt needs to be
  updated with the file which is put in target during the build (though the
  header at the top should remain, with the version updated.</para>

  <para>The geomajas-dep pom and aggregate.sh need to be updated for the
  released and new snapshot versions respectively.</para>

  <para>Remember to comment the snapshot repository in all poms.</para>

  <para>The documentation uses the example applications for extracting code
  which is included in the manual. This is a circular dependency when it
  includes the part to be released. It may be useful to do a local build using
  the next release version locally, to allow the release the work for the
  documentation part. You can do the actual release of the example application
  at the end.</para>

  <para>When releasing the backend core, there may be a problem building the
  javadocs. The solution can be to do a local build of the backend using the
  next release version before doing the actual release.</para>

  <para>When releasing the GWT face, make sure the dependency versions are
  correct in
  <code>geomajas-gwt-archetype/src/main/resources/archetype-resources/pom.xml</code>.</para>

  <para>Close the staging repository (which makes the artifacts available for
  testing). When staging several parts, it is recommended to close each
  separately. This allows more fine-grained promotion and/or dropping of
  artifacts.</para>

  <para>When staging is done and the repository closed, start a vote to allow
  users to test the new artifact.</para>

  <para>When the vote failed, drop the repository. Development just continue
  and the version number is skipped. The release data in JIRA is actually the
  staging date.</para>

  <para>When the vote was successful, promote the staged artifacts and
  announce the release, for the back-end, this requires the following
  steps:</para>

  <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
    <listitem>
      <para>Upload zip files to sourceforge download area</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>JIRA: Assure the next version exists, mark the current version as
      released agreeing to move open issue to the next version.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>For unstable release: install gwt-example for online trial</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>For stable release: install all demo application for online
      trial</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Announce:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Build announcement message using the following
            template:</para>

            <blockquote>
              <para>title: Geomajas <emphasis>1.5.0</emphasis>
              <emphasis>technology preview/release candidate/stable
              </emphasis> released</para>

              <para></para>

              <para>The Geomajas project is proud to release Geomajas 1.5.0, a
              technology preview showcasing the progress we are making towards
              our next stable build.</para>

              <para>The major advances in this version include
              <emphasis>(indicate major contributors when
              appropriate)</emphasis></para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>modularization of the system</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>introduction of a GWT face</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

              <para>For the full list of changes, see
              http://jira.geomajas.org/jira/secure/ReleaseNote.jspa?version=10131&amp;styleName=Html&amp;projectId=10000&amp;Create=Create</para>

              <para>Documentation for this release can be found at
              http://files.geomajas.org/maven/1.5.0/geomajas/userguide.html
              .</para>

              <para>Download links can be found at
              http://geomajas.org/release_1.5.0 .</para>

              <para>For the next release we plan to include the following
              features</para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>absorb CO2 from the air to reduce global
                  warming</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>remove need for system to be powered</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>

              <para></para>

              <para>Please note that this is an unstable release, all the new
              features since the previous stable release may still change and
              we some new bugs may have been introduced.</para>

              <para>If you want to help us, join the discussions on the
              developer list, list bugs in jira and make feature requests in
              our fora. See http://www.geomajas.org/gis-development .</para>

              <para></para>

              <para>Geomajas is the extensible open source web mapping
              framework, enabling integrated GIS solutions for businesses and
              government.</para>
            </blockquote>

            <para>Feel free to change wording and add useful content.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create download image for this version (278x61
            pixels).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Add release on download page (remember to name the page
            "release_1.5.0" with correct version number).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For a stable release, update the documentation page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For a stable release, update Geomajas wikipedia page.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Send announcement to majas-dev (plain text).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Publish on general forum.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Create news item (without the "Geomajas is..."
            footer.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Send mail to jan.pote@geosparc.com to assure Geosparc is
            informed of the release.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para></para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
</chapter>
