<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-configuration">
  <title>Configuration</title>

  <para>Configuration for the geocoder plugin.</para>

  <section id="dependencies">
    <title>Dependencies</title>

    <para>Make sure sure you include the correct version of the plugin in
    your project. Use the following excerpt (with the correct version) in the
    dependencyManagement section of your project:</para>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting> &lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.project&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-project-server&lt;/artifactId&gt;
    &lt;version&gt;<?eval ${project.version}?>&lt;/version&gt;
    &lt;type&gt;pom&lt;/type&gt;
    &lt;scope&gt;import&lt;/scope&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;
</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <para>If you are using geomajas-dep, this includes the latest released
    version of the caching plugin (at the time of publishing of that
    version). If you want to overwrite the caching plugin version, make sure
    to include this excerpt <emphasis>before</emphasis> the geomajas-dep
    dependency.</para>

    <para>You can now include the actual dependency without explicit
    version.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Plugin dependency</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.plugin&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-plugin-geocoder&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>
    </example>

  </section>

  <section id="staticregex">
    <title>Static regex geocoder service configuration</title>

    <para>The StaticRegexGeocoderService allows you to define the combinations
    of string to match and the locations directly in the configuration
    file.</para>

    <para>The strings to match are specified using regular
    expressions<footnote>
        <para>see <ulink
        url="http://download.oracle.com/javase/1.4.2/docs/api/java/util/regex/Pattern.html">http://download.oracle.com/javase/1.4.2/docs/api/java/util/regex/Pattern.html</ulink></para>
      </footnote>to allow more flexibility. Listing <xref
    linkend="RegexGeocoderInfo" /> shows a base configuration. You have to use
    the geocoderInfo property to configure the geolocator. This is done using
    a StaticRegexGeocoderInfo object which contains the coordinate space name
    (EPSG:900913 in this case, which is Mercator) and define the location
    mappings.</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/RegexGeocoderInfo.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>The location mappings themselves are contained in
    StaticRegexGeocoderLocationInfo instances. You have to specify the strings
    toMatch, and a location as either point of bounding box. You can specify
    the canonical form for the search.</para>

    <para>In listing <xref linkend="RegexPoint" /> you see a definition which
    will match a single location string starting with second. As this is done
    case independently, some examples of matching strings are "second" and
    SECondary". It indicates a point with coordinates (10000,10000).</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/RegexPoint.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>The location info object can also be used to match an area. In
    listing <xref linkend="RegexBbox" /> you see the location bounding box
    defined using the bbox property. If you would accidentally define both a
    bounding box and point coordinates, then the bounding box will be used for
    the result.</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/RegexBbox.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>A location can also include extra data in the result. You need to
    wrap this data in a subclass of ClientUserDataInfo. The object to be
    returned can be defined using the userData property.</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/RegexBboxUserData.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>The toMatch property contains a list of strings which need to be
    matched in order. The matching checks every string in the location strings
    for a matching string in the toMatch list, in order. The matching is case
    independent and always matches the entire string. A level can be marked as
    optional in the location strings by using a question marks as prefix for
    the regular expression. The question mark is removed before the actual
    evaluation of the regular expression.</para>

    <para>As an example we will apply the example in listing <xref
    linkend="RegexMulti" /> to a couple of data sets.</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>["Belgium", "Antwerpen", "Booischot"]: matches, all three
          parts match the specific regular expressions.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>["Booischot", "Antwerpen", "Belgium"]: no match as the "BE.*"
          regular expression does not match "Booischot".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>["BE", "Booischot"]: matches, the "Antwerp.*" regular
          expression is marked as option using the "?" prefix.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>["Belgium","Antwerpen"]: does not match as the "Booischot"
          regular expression is not matched for lack of input strings.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>["Belgium", "Antwerpen", "Booischot", "Broekmansstraat"]: not
          matches as the last string "Broekmansstraat" does not have a
          matching regular expression.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <xi:include href="listing/RegexMulti.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>For this last case, where smaller divisions are not know (in this
    case the street name), you can end the list of regular expressions with
    "**" (see listing <xref linkend="RegexMultiOpenEnd" />). This will assure
    that any remaining strings from the input are discarded if any are
    remaining. This would assure that the last case in the previous list
    matches. The other cases would still have the same result.</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/RegexMultiOpenEnd.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section id="geonames">
    <title>GeoNames service configuration</title>

    <para>The GeonamesGeocoderService uses the search web service at
    geonames.org to handle the geocoder requests. You can only configure the
    "userName" property which is the geonames user which is registered to
    access the service. This can either be passed directly or using the
    "userNameProperty" which indicates the property which contains the user
    name to use. Defining the service is pretty straightforward.</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/GeonamesConfiguration.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>The GeoNames service never returns more than 50 results.</para>

    <para>When the initial query returned no results, it will retry the search
    using fuzzy matching.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="placefinder">
    <title>Yahoo! PlaceFinder geocoder service configuration</title>

    <para>This uses the Yahoo! PlaceFinder service (<ulink
    url="http://developer.yahoo.com/geo/placefinder/">http://developer.yahoo.com/geo/placefinder/</ulink>).
    When using this geocoder, you need a appid from Yahoo! and you have to
    make sure you comply with their terms of use.</para>

    <para>To use the geocoder, just create the bean and set the appId.</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/PlaceFinderConfig.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>There are a couple of properties which influence how the appId can
    be passed:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>appId</emphasis>: you just define the appId in the
          configuration file.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>appIdProperty</emphasis>: the appId is read from the
          property which is specified. This can be helpful if you don't want
          to hardcode the property in your configuration files for some
          reason.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>skipAppIdCheck</emphasis>: normally an exception is
          thrown when the Yahoo! PlaceFinder geocoder is created without a
          appId. By setting this property to true, you can avoid this
          exception, making sure your application will run without the appId
          (though obviously no results can be found).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="geocoderService">
    <title>Type coordinate geocoder service configuration</title>

    <para>This is a simplistic geocoder which allows the user to directly type
    the coordinate. To configure it, you just have to supply the
    default CRS used for the coordinates (if not specified, this defaults to
    EPSG:4326).</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/TypeCoordinate.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para>The service accepts input strings like "4.77397 51.05125" to jump to
    a coordinate, using a space is used as separator between the ordinates.
    This uses the defaultCrs as configured. You can also explicitly specify
    the CRS by using a string like "4.77397 51.05125 crs:EPSG:4326".</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
