<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-configuration">
  <title>Configuration</title>

  <para>Apart from the maven dependency configuration, most of the
  configuration options of the printing plugin are currently provided by the
  end user at runtime. To provide access to the plugin's functionality from
  the GWT face, an action has been provided that pops up a printing
  preferences window.</para>

  <section id="dependencies">
    <title>Dependency configuration</title>

    <para>To use the printing plugin, you have to include the plug-in
    dependencies in your pom. When using this in the GWT face and you already
    have a dependency on geomajas-dep version 1.10.36 or higher, you can
    declare this as :</para>

    <example>
      <title>printing plug-in dependency for GWT face using
      geomajas-dep</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.plugin&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-plugin-printing-gwt&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>
    </example>

    <para>When not using the version from geomajas-dep, you may need to
    declare versions for both the back-end part of the plug-in and the GWT
    face part.</para>

    <xi:include href="listing/PrintingDependency.xml"
                xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

    <para />
  </section>

  <section id="gwtface">
    <title>GWT face configuration</title>

    <section id="gwtmodule">
      <title>GWT module definition</title>

      <para>In order to be able to use the printing plug-in in a GWT
      application, you will need to include the GWT module for the printing
      plug-in in your applications GWT module definition. In order to do this,
      add the following configuration line to your applications .gwt.xml
      file:</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/PrintingGwtModule.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <para>This will make the GWT widgets and their source (assuming you have
      the jars on the classpath) available for the GWT compiler.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="gwttoolbar">
      <title>Example toolbar configuration</title>

      <para>To use the printing functionality in a map, the following
      <code>ClientToolInfo</code> bean should be added to the map's
      toolbar:</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/PrintingToolInfo.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <para>The name of the <code>ClientToolInfo</code> bean should be exactly
      as spelled in the above program listing.</para>

      <para>If configured correctly, the following tool icon will show up in
      the toolbar:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Toolbar icon for printing</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/print.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
