<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-usage">
  <title>Usage</title>

  <para>To start using the printing functionality, the user should activate
  the printing tool in the toolbar by clicking the tool button
  (<inlinemediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/print.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </inlinemediaobject>).</para>

  <para>The following printing preferences dialog will now appear:</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Printing preferences dialog</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/printing-preferences.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The user can customize the PDF print according to the following
  options:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Title: textbox that allows the user to add an optional title to
      the print. The title appears centered at the top.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Size: dropdown box to choose the page size, defaults to A4</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Orientation: landscape or portrait orientation</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Show north arrow: if checked, a north arrow will be added at the
      upper right of the map</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Show scale bar: if checked, a scalebar will be added at the lower
      left of the map</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Raster DPI: slidebar to choose a DPI value for raster layers. The
      DPI (Dots Per Inch) value, or - more correctly, but less generally known
      - PPI (Pixel Per Inch) value, indicates the number of pixels that will
      be used per inch in the print. In general, good resolution printing
      requires a value of at least 300-400 PP, much more than the average
      screen resolution. PDF size and rendering time will increase
      proportionally with the square of the DPI.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Dowload method: the PDF document can be saved on the file system
      or immediately opened in the browser. The latter option requires the
      user to allow popups for the main page.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Status: an activity bar to indicate printing progress. The
      activity bar does not show real progress as it is impossible to
      determine the file size or rendering time up front.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>After configuring the preferences, the user should click the print
  button to start printing. This initiates the following proces:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>A printing command is sent to the server</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The PDF document is generated in-memory and a unique key is
      returned to the client. During this stage, the activity bar is activated
      <inlinegraphic fileref="images/pleasewait.gif" /></para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>The client fetches the PDF by opening a URL with the generated key
      as parameter, either in a new window or in an invisible iframe (for
      download to the file system).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The final result looks as follows:</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Example print</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/printing-sample.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</chapter>
