<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<appendix id="cla" lang="en">
  <title>Geomajas Contributor License Agreement</title>

  <para>In order for N.V. Geosparc (hereinafter “Geosparc”), a company under
  Belgian Law having its registered office at Gaston Crommenlaan 10, box 101,
  9050, Gent, Belgium which is registered at the commercial register in Ghent,
  n° 0808.353.458, to have a clear understanding on the intellectual property
  rights associated with the Geomajas software library (hereinafter “Geomajas
  Project”) and to clearly determine the responsibilities and obligations
  associated with the Contributions (as defined hereinafter), Geosparc must
  receive a signed Geomajas Contributor License Agreement of the Contributor
  (as defined hereinafter) indicating that the Contributor agrees with the
  terms and conditions as defined hereunder. This Geomajas Contributor License
  Agreement (hereinafter “the Agreement”) intends to protect the Contributor
  as well as Geosparc.</para>

  <para>Contributor hereby accepts and agrees to the following terms and
  conditions with regard to past, current and future Contributions submitted
  by Contributor to Geosparc, and has accepted the policy “Geomajas
  Contributions Policy”</para>

  <para></para>

  <section id="CLA-def">
    <title>Definitions</title>

    <para>When used in this Agreement the following words and or expressions
    shall have the meaning as stated hereunder unless the context expressly
    requires otherwise:</para>

    <para><orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>“Contributor” means 1/ any individual and/or legal entity that
          voluntarily submits (a) Contribution(s) to the Geomajas Project or
          2/ any individual legally representing his/her Company.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>“Contribution” means any original work, including any
          modification and/or addition to the existing work that is submitted
          for introduction in, or documentation of, any of the products owned
          or managed by Geosparc, where such work originates from a
          Contributor. A Contribution may be submitted in any form of
          electronic, verbal and/or written communication or documentation,
          including without limitation, communication on electronic mailing
          lists, source code control systems and issue tracking systems that
          are managed by or on behalf of Geosparc for the purpose of
          discussion and improving the results of the Geomajas Project.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="CLA-repr">
    <title>Granted Rights - Representations</title>

    <para><orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>For the benefit of Geosparc, the Contributor hereby:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>irrevocably assigns, transfers and conveys to Geosparc all
              right, title and interest in and to the Contribution(s).  Such
              assignment includes copyrights (to the extent permitted by
              applicable mandatory law) and all other intellectual property
              rights other than patents and patent applications (“Patent”),
              together with all causes of actions accrued in favour for
              infringement thereof, recognized by any jurisdiction
              (“Proprietary Rights”).  Without limitation of the foregoing,
              Geosparc shall be entitled to determine in its sole discretion
              whether or not to use the Contribution(s) and to use, sell,
              distribute, license, re-produce, re-use, modify, update, edit or
              otherwise make available the Contribution(s) as it sees fit, in
              any manner currently known or in the future discovered and for
              any and all purposes;</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>grants (to the extent that under applicable mandatory law,
              Proprietary Rights cannot be assigned, transferred or conveyed)
              to Geosparc and to the recipients of the software incorporating
              the Contribution(s) an irrevocable, worldwide, non-exclusive,
              fully paid-up and royalty-free copyright license to reproduce,
              modify, prepare derivative works of, (publicly) display,
              perform, sub license and distribute the Contribution(s);</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>grants to Geosparc and to recipients of software
              distributed by Geosparc a worldwide, non-exclusive, fully
              paid-up, royalty-free, irrevocable (except as stated in this
              Agreement) Patent license to make, have made, use, offer to
              sell, sell, import, and otherwise transfer the Contribution(s),
              where such license applies only to the Patent claims licensable
              by Contributor that are necessarily infringed by the
              Contributor’s Contribution(s) alone or by combination of such
              Contribution(s) with other work of Geosparc.  Contributor
              furthermore agrees to immediately notify Geosparc of any patents
              that Contributor knows or comes to know are likely infringed by
              the Contribution(s) and/or are not licensable by the
              Contributor. If any entity institutes patent litigation against
              the Contributor or any other entity (including a cross-claim or
              counterclaim in a lawsuit) alleging that Contributor’s
              Contribution(s) or the Geomajas Project work to which the
              Contributor has contributed constitutes direct or contributory
              patent infringement, then any Patent licenses granted under this
              Agreement for that Contribution or Geomajas Project work shall
              immediately terminate as of the date such litigation is
              filed.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Upon the assignment of the Proprietary Rights and the grant of
          the license as set forth in this article 2, Geosparc hereby grants a
          non-exclusive, worldwide, fully-paid up, royalty-free license to
          make, use reproduce, distribute, modify and prepare derivative works
          based on the Contribution(s) of Contributor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Contributor hereby represents and warrants that:</para>

          <para><orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>In the case that the Contributor is an individual who
                works in his/her own name the Contributor guarantees that
                he/she is legally entitled to assign the Proprietary Rights
                and to grant the above license.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>In the case that the Contributor is an employee the
                Contributor guarantees that he/she can legally represent the
                Company and is entitled to assign the Proprietary Rights and
                to grant the above license.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>In the case the Contributor is a Company and the
                Contributor’s employee(s) or consultant(s) have rights to
                intellectual property the Contributor warrants that its
                employee(s) has waived such rights;</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>each Contribution is the original creation of the
                Contributor.  Contributor represents that each submission of a
                contribution includes complete details of any third-party
                license or other restrictions of which you are aware and which
                are associated with any part of the Contribution(s);</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>no claim or dispute has been threatened or filed in
                connection with the ownership, use or distribution of the
                Contribution(s); and</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>the execution of this Agreement does not constitute a
                breach under any other agreement to which Contributor and/or
                its employer is a party, does not require the consent,
                approval or waiver from or notice to any third party and does
                not violate any law or regulation.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist></para>

          <para>Contributor shall immediately inform Geosparc of any facts
          and/or circumstances of which Contributor becomes aware that would
          make the representations and warranties inaccurate or untrue in any
          respect.</para>

          <para>Contributor further agrees that Contributor shall at no time
          hereafter dispute, contest or aid or assist third party in disputing
          and/or contesting, either directly or indirectly, the right, title
          and interest in any and all Contributions of Geosparc as detailed in
          this Agreement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In case that under applicable mandatory law the Contributor
          retains the moral rights or other inalienable rights to the
          Contributions, the Contributor agrees not to exercise such rights
          without the prior written permission of Geosparc.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In order to ensure that Geosparc will be able to acquire, use
          and protect its Proprietary Rights as detailed in this article 2,
          Contributor will (i) sign any documents to assist Geosparc in the
          documentation, perfection and enforcement of its rights, and (ii)
          provide Geosparc with support and reasonable access to information
          for applying, securing, protecting, perfecting and enforcing its
          rights.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
  </section>

  <section id="CLA-warranties">
    <title>Warranties</title>

    <para>EXCEPT FOR THE EXPRESS WARRANTIES DETAILED IN ARTICLE 2, THE
    CONTRIBUTION(S) ARE PROVIDED “AS IS” AND NEITHER CONTRIBUTOR NOR THE
    Geosparc MAKES ANY WARRANTIES OF ANY KIND TO THE OTHER PARTY, EITHER
    EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING WITHOUT LIMITATION OF ANY WARRANTY OF
    MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="CLA-misc">
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>

    <para><orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>This Agreement shall enter into force upon execution of this
          document by Contributor.  This Agreement may be terminated by a
          party if the other party commits a breach of this Agreement provided
          that if the breach is capable of remedy termination shall not occur
          if the breach shall not have been remedied within 90 days of such
          other party having been given notice in writing specifying the
          breach and requiring it to be remedied.  The termination of this
          Agreement shall however remain in full force and effect with respect
          to any Contribution submitted prior to the termination date of the
          Agreement.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>This Agreement contains the entire agreement between the
          parties and supersedes all prior or contemporaneous agreements or
          understanding, whether written or oral, relating to its subject
          matter.  If any provision of this Agreement shall be deemed invalid
          or unenforceable, the validity and enforceability of the remaining
          provisions of this Agreement shall not be affected and such
          provision shall be deemed modified only to the extent necessary to
          make such provision consistent with applicable law.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>4.3.The Agreement is governed by the laws of Belgium, without
          reference to its conflict of law principles.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Geosparc shall have the right to assign its rights and
          obligations hereunder to any successor or assignee of its business
          or assets to which this Agreement relates, whether by merger,
          establishment of a legal entity, acquisition, operation of law or
          otherwise without the prior written consent of the
          Contributor.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Please execute (2) original copies of the above document and send
    this to the following recipient:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Address of recipient</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Geosparc</para>

    <para>Gaston Crommenlaan 10/101</para>

    <para>BE-9050 Ghent</para>

    <para>BELGIUM</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>The Contributor:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Name:</para>

    <para>Title (if applicable in case of legal entity):</para>

    <para>Full name of legal entity and address registered office (if
    applicable):</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Date:</para>

    <para>Signature:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>The Company:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Name:</para>

    <para>Title (if applicable in case of legal entity):</para>

    <para>Full name of legal entity and address registered office (if
    applicable):</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>Date:</para>

    <para>Signature:</para>

    <para></para>

    <para></para>

    <para>N.V. Geosparc – Register N° BE 0808.353.458</para>
  </section>
</appendix>
