<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="developers" lang="en">
  <title>Developers information</title>

  <section id="maveninfo">
    <title>maven compilation, targets, profiles, variables</title>

    <para>When doing an initial compilation of Geomajas, you may need to start
    compilation from the "build-tools" and then the "backend" directories.
    Only when these are compiled, compilation from the project root will
    succeed.</para>

    <programlisting>cd build-tools
mvn install
cd backend
mvn install
cd ..
mvn install</programlisting>

    <para>The source contains one main pom which allows building of the
    Geomajas framework and each of the sample applications in one go.</para>

    <para>You can also choose to build them individually.</para>

    <para>There are a couple of profiles defined which should help during
    development:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><code>-DskipShrink</code>: do not use shrinking when building or
        using the dojo face. When not specified, a shrinked version of the
        javascript files is used. The files are compressed and combined for
        faster loading and better caching.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>-DskipDocs: do not build the documentation module. Can speed up
        the build a little.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>-DskipGwt: skip the GWT compilation phases. Useful when you just
        want a quick compile or don't want/need the compile to
        JavaScript.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-Dfull-build</code>: from the root project, this enables
        inclusion of the build tools and documentation in the build. This is
        actually enabled by default (to disable use
        <code>-Dhudson</code>"),</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><code>-Dhudson</code>: profile for running the selenium
        integration tests on the Jenkins (previously Hudson) continuous integration server. As long
        as running the tests on the ci server proves problematic, this will
        disable these tests.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para></para>

    <section id="GWTbuild">
      <title>GWT build</title>

      <para>For faster compilation during testing (when not using development
      mode), it can be useful to compile only for the browser used for
      testing. This will reduce the number of compilation steps by a factor 6.
      Removing supported languages can further remove compilation steps.
      Include the following excerpt in your <code>Xxx.gwt.xml</code> file to
      set your target browser.</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;!-- set target browser to compile for, use this to limit to the browser used for testing --&gt;
&lt;!-- where value = "ie6/opera/gecko1_8/safari/gecko" , "gecko1_8" is FireFox 3 --&gt;
&lt;set-property name="user.agent" value="gecko1_8" /&gt;</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section id="dojobuild">
      <title>dojo build</title>

      <para>For development using the dojo face, apart from using the
      "-DskipShrink" setting mentioned higher, you may also want to configure
      the ResourceController to try to directly read the JavaScript files from
      disk before looking at the classpath (it also changes the cache
      headers). This allows a simple refresh in the browser to load the
      changed versions. You can configure this using a init-param for the
      dispatcher servlet, like in this example.</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;servlet&gt;
    &lt;servlet-name&gt;dispatcher&lt;/servlet-name&gt;
    &lt;servlet-class&gt;org.springframework.web.servlet.DispatcherServlet&lt;/servlet-class&gt;
    &lt;init-param&gt;
        &lt;param-name&gt;files-location&lt;/param-name&gt;
        &lt;param-value&gt;/home/me/apps/java/geomajas/geomajas/geomajas-dojo-client/src/main/resources&lt;/param-value&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;
            When this is specified, files are searched here first.
            Files which are found at this locations are not cached.
        &lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/init-param&gt;
    &lt;init-param&gt;
        &lt;param-name&gt;contextConfigLocation&lt;/param-name&gt;
        &lt;param-value&gt;classpath*:META-INF/geomajasWebContext.xml&lt;/param-value&gt;
        &lt;description&gt;Spring Web-MVC specific (additional) context files.&lt;/description&gt;
    &lt;/init-param&gt;
    &lt;load-on-startup&gt;3&lt;/load-on-startup&gt;
&lt;/servlet&gt;
</programlisting></para>
    </section>

    <section id="runexample">
      <title>Running the example applications</title>

      <para>Once you have done a "<code>mvn install</code>" on either the
      entire tree or the "Geomajas" directory, you can use maven to run the
      example applications.</para>

      <para>For the dojo face, you can run the examples using (when in the
      geomajas-dojo-example directory) <programlisting>mvn jetty:run</programlisting></para>

      <para>For the gwt face, you have three options. Once in the
      geomajas-gwt-simple directory, you can run the application in
      development mode using <programlisting>mvn gwt:run</programlisting></para>

      <note>
        <para>Due to classpath problems and the gwt-maven-plugin which does
        not properly handle excluded dependencies (the "provided" scope), this
        can fail on some systems.</para>
      </note>

      <para>You can also use jetty to run the normally built
      application<programlisting>mvn jetty:run</programlisting></para>

      <para>Alternatively you can run the actual war using <programlisting>mvn jetty:run-war</programlisting><note>
          <para>It can be advisable to run "mvn clean" between "gwt:run" and
          "jetty:run-war" or the classpath problem from the previous footnote
          may appear again.</para>
        </note></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="docs">
    <title>Documentation</title>

    <para>The general documentation is split in three books.</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>developers guide: guide for developer who want to use Geomajas
          in their application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>contributors guide: guide for people who want to contribute to
          the project or want to know more about the functioning of the
          project (this one).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>end user guide: documentation for end users of applications
          built using Geomajas.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>Apart from that, each face and each plug-in has their own
    documentation.</para>

    <para>All documentation is written in docbook format to allow both PDF and
    HTML output formats. The sources can be found in the "documentation"
    directory of the project.</para>

    <para>For editing the docbook files, we recommend using <ulink
    url="http://www.xmlmind.com/xmleditor/">XMLMind</ulink>. The personal
    version is free and can (at the time of writing) be used for editing open
    source documentation.</para>

    <para>The docbook files are currently formatted using XMLMind. When using
    another tool for editing, please keep the current formatting to assure
    diffs remain usable.</para>

    <para>The documentation includes a lot of examples which are excerpts from
    the source of the example applications. This prevents copy-paste mistakes.
    The build process for the documentation automatically updates these
    excepts. The directories which have to be scanned for excepts are
    specified in the pom. When this includes code which is not in the current
    versioned entity (the root directory for the face or plug-in), then the
    source needs to be obtained from a dependency and unpacked. Excerpts can
    be annotated using annotations like</para>

    <para><programlisting>&lt;!-- @extract-start AllowAllSecurity, Allow full access to everybody --&gt;
&lt;bean name="security.securityInfo" class="org.geomajas.security.SecurityInfo"&gt;
    &lt;property name="loopAllServices" value="false"/&gt;
&lt;/bean&gt;
&lt;!-- @extract-end --&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>for XML or</para>

    <para><programlisting>// @extract-start filename, title
for (String line : lines) {
    // do something
}
// @extract-end</programlisting></para>

    <para>for java files. The start annotation includes the filename which
    should be used (all files are placed in the "listing" directory) and
    optionally a title for the example.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="APIcontract">
    <title>API contract</title>

    <para>The Geomajas project has a very strong API contract. To assure the
    project adheres to this contract, we have the following
    requirements;</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>No API classes or interfaces may be removed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No API classes or interfaces may be renamed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No API classes or interfaces may have their package name
          modified.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No API methods may be removed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No API methods may have their signature changed.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>No methods may be added to classes annotated using
          "<code>@<code>UserImplemented</code></code>".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Each class on which a "@Api" annotation is added should have a
          "@since" javadoc comment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Each method on which a "@Api" annotation is added should have
          a "@since" javadoc comment.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Each public method which is added in a class which is
          annotated with "@Api(allMethods = true)", should have a "@since"
          javadoc comment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>The checkstyle configuration which is used for the project (which is
    defined in the geomajas-parent parent) tries to check the API contract.
    This required a api.txt file in src/main/resources which contains the API
    for the previous release version. The API for the compiled version is put
    in target/api.txt.</para>

    <para>Note that apart from the class and method signatures, the behaviour
    should also remain constant (especially when documented or tested). Just
    keep a method and throwing <code>NotImplementedException</code> cannot be
    considered "maintaining a stable API".</para>
  </section>

  <section id="versioning">
    <title>Versioning</title>

    <para>Version have a major.minor.patch structure.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
         major: indicates that this release has major advances over previous releases. New major versions do not need to be backwards compatible. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         minor: indicates that there are important new features that do not break compatibility with previous versions with the same major number. Even minor versions are used for "stable" versions which will be supported by Geosparc. Odd minor versions are used for work-in-progress and stabilisation efforts. 
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
         patch: bugfixes and smaller improvements. 
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="commits">
    <title>subversion, commits</title>

    <para>New committers need to sign an agreement which hands over copyright
    to Geosparc. Policies are needed for assigning commit rights (see
    below).</para>

    <para>All SVN commits should include the JIRA issue number at the start of
    the commit message, and a short description of the work done. The JIRA
    issue number allows linking the commits with the issues (as can be seen in
    JIRA), the short message allows persons to know what is happening without
    referring to JIRA. The only times JIRA issue number are not needed is for
    making "obvious" changes like fixing typos.</para>

    <para>Commits should be grouped by issue as much as possible/sensible
    (better two commits than one commit for fixing two issues, better one
    commit of five files than five commits of one file (for one
    issue)).</para>

    <para>Development of the "latest-and-greatest" version happens in
    "trunk".</para>

    <para>Continued development on earlier versions (when not
    "latest-and-greatest") occur in branches with the future version number as
    name.</para>

    <para>When a release is cut, a tag with the release version as name is
    created. The release should be built from the tagged files.</para>

    <para>After each commit, the system should still compile and all test
    cases should still succeed. There is a continuous integration engine
    (Jenkins) which verifies this and send messages to the commit mailing list
    on failures.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="coding">
    <title>Coding</title>

    <para>Note that details about coding style and naming are on the <xref
    linkend="codingstyle">coding style</xref> page.</para>

    <section id="logging">
      <title>Logging</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>When inserting debug statements, parameterized messages should
          be used to prevent the need/usefulness of
          <code>isDebugEnabled()</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           all logging is done through slf4f, logger is created using 

          <programlisting>private final Logger log = LoggerFactory.getLogger( ContainingClassName.class );</programlisting>

           
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           logging levels 

          <table>
            <title>logging levels</title>

            <tgroup cols="3">
              <thead>
                <row>
                  <entry align="center">log level</entry>

                  <entry align="center">default on</entry>

                  <entry>use</entry>
                </row>
              </thead>

              <tbody>
                <row>
                  <entry>ERROR</entry>

                  <entry>yes</entry>

                  <entry>major problems, should always be visible in logs and
                  are likely to require action from a person (to fix the
                  condition or assure it does not happen again). Indicates
                  that something is seriously wrong.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>WARN</entry>

                  <entry>yes</entry>

                  <entry>warning about potential problems. Should always be
                  visible in logs and a person will probably need to assess
                  whether this is harmless or should be treated as an
                  error.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>INFO</entry>

                  <entry>yes</entry>

                  <entry>important information. You can assume this level is
                  on in production, so it should be carefully considered
                  whether this level is appropriate. In general only used to
                  indicate service status (started, stopped).</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>DEBUG</entry>

                  <entry>no</entry>

                  <entry>logging information which is detailed enough to know
                  what is happening in the system, without flooding the
                  logs.</entry>
                </row>

                <row>
                  <entry>TRACE</entry>

                  <entry>no</entry>

                  <entry>very detailed logging, probably only making sense to
                  the developer of the code.</entry>
                </row>
              </tbody>
            </tgroup>
          </table>

           
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           When an exception is caught and (another exception) thrown you should not log the exception. You should however include the cause in the newly thrown exception. 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="unittesting">
      <title>Unit testing</title>

      <para>Unit testing: At least each class implementing the public API
      should have a unit test, testing all methods. For testing JUnit is
      used.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
           Advantages of unit testing: 

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Capturing a <ulink
              url="http://jira.geomajas.org/">JIRA</ulink> bug report in a
              reproducible manner.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>Allowing you to specify exactly the behaviour you want,
            before you start coding.</listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

           
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           How unit testing should be done: 

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>If you are testing
            src/main/java/org/geomajas/ToBeTestedClass.java, create a class
            src/test/java/org/geomajas/ToBeTestedClassTest.java. Actual test
            methods have a name starting with "test". The class itself should
            extend jnit.framework.TestCase.</listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The test will automatically be run when running "<code>mvn
              install</code>".</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

           
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
           Integration tests should also be provided. These can also be used for testing the user interface (thanks to selenium). 
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="exceptionhandling">
      <title>Exception handling</title>

      <para>*Never* throw away exception, either log them or throw them again
      (possibly wrapped). Do not log and throw, this only clutters log files
      with duplicate exceptions.</para>

      <para>Do not wrap exceptions unnecessarily (so no
      <code>GeomajasException</code> caused by a
      <code>GeomajasException</code>) unless you add additional information in
      the message.</para>

      <para>When wrapping an exception, always include the cause.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="refactoring">
      <title>Refactoring</title>

      <para>Changes in the (public) API use a "deprecate, then remove" cycle.
      It should be marked "deprecated" in at least one minor version before it
      can be removed in the next major version.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="fileencoding">
      <title>File encoding</title>

      <para>All source files, including .properties files should use UTF-8
      encoding.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="dev-other">
      <title>Other</title>

      <para>For the directory structure and file locations, we follow standard
      maven conventions (see
      http://maven.apache.org/guides/introduction/introduction-to-the-standard-directory-layout.html).</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
