<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="jira" lang="en">
  <title>JIRA conventions</title>

  <section id="jira-basics">
    <title>Basic issue tracker rules</title>

    <section id="jira-opoi">
      <title>One problem one issue</title>

      <para>When you report a problem, please submit one issue per problem.
      There are various reasons for this, amongst them:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The more crowded an issue is, the more likely is it that some
          problems may get lost over time.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Different problems are likely to be handled by different
          people. The more problems you put into the issue, the more difficult
          is this issue to handle for all involved parties.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In particular, if you're going to write sentences like "Besides
      this, I noticed that..." or "There are several problems with....", then
      please seriously ask yourself whether you should submit multiple issues
      instead of a single one.</para>

      <para>If you don't follow this rule, be prepared for people asking you
      to split up your issue.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="jira-summary">
      <title>Provide a meaningful summary</title>

      <para>Providing a meaningful summary helps the committers to easily
      recognize an issue in a list of dozens of others. Since duplicate issues
      are draining a lot of work from committers, you should always check if
      the issue you wish to report hasn't already been reported. Of course
      this works best if the summaries of the existing issues are as
      descriptive as possible.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="jira-desc">
      <title>Provide a clear description</title>

      <para>You, as the submitter of a problem, know exactly what you were
      doing when you were hit by the problem. However, most other people
      probably don't. For instance, they may have a completely different
      workflow for doing the same things you are doing.</para>

      <para>In order to prevent committers to have to ask back how exactly an
      issue can be reproduced, it is the task of the issue's submitter to be
      as clear on this as possible - preferably by given a step-by-step
      description.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="jira-form">
    <title>Filling out the JIRA form</title>

    <para>In order to create a new issue, you need to log in to the <ulink
    url="http://jira.geomajas.org/">JIRA issue tracker</ulink>.</para>

    <para>When creating a new issue, the first thing you will be asked, is to
    select the project and issue type:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Project: the project you wish to report an issue for (please try
        to use the correct module, only use the Geomajas when it doesn't fit a
        specific module - if it fits multiple modules, please add to
        all).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Issue Type: the type of issue you want to report. Is it a bug,
        task or a question? Please be correct in this.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Then a new form appears with new fields to fill in. The summary and
    description have been discussed earlier. As for the other fields:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Priority: how urgent is the issue? This value can always be
        changed by the Geomajas committers if they feel that the priority does
        not match the issue's impact.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Due date: not used.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Components: What component do you think the issue relates to?
        Not necessary to fill this in.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Affects version: In what version of Geomajas did you encounter
        the issue?</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Assignee: Assign the issue to someone you believe is best suited
        to fix the issue.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>CLA: Whether you agree to the CLA. This needs to be ticked when
        you include a patch with the issue and haven't sent a signed CLA to
        the project.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The rest is not used.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>
