<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2012 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="getting-started">
  <title>Starting a new GWT based Geomajas project</title>

  <para>Geomajas uses the Apache Maven project management tool for its build
  and documentation process. Thanks to Maven , the easiest way to start using
  Geomajas is by creating a new project using the Maven archetype. This will
  create a simple working project that you can use as starting point.</para>

  <section id="prereq">
    <title>Prerequisites / Command line</title>

    <para>As the simple project is created using the Maven archetype, you will
    need to install Maven on your system, which can be downloaded from <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org/">http://maven.apache.org/</ulink>. We
    recommend using the latest stable version (2.2.1 at the time of writing).
    Installing Maven is quite simple: just unzip the distribution file in the
    directory of your choice and make some environment changes so you can
    access the executable. More information for your specific OS can be found
    at the bottom of <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org/download.html">http://maven.apache.org/download.html</ulink>.</para>

    <section id="templ">
      <title>Creating the template project</title>

      <para>At this point it is assumed that Maven has been successfully
      installed. Using Maven, you can now create a template project, called
      the Geomajas GWT Application Archetype.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step1</emphasis>: Go to the folder you want to
          create this application in, and execute the following
          command:</para>

          <example>
            <title>Create project using GWT Maven archetype</title>
            <programlisting>mvn archetype:generate -DarchetypeCatalog=http://files.geomajas.org/archetype-catalog.xml</programlisting>
          </example>

          <para>This will create the template project, using the latest stable
          release. If you want to use the latest snapshot, use the following
          command instead:</para>

          <example>
            <title>Create project using GWT Maven archetype</title>
            <programlisting>mvn archetype:generate -DarchetypeCatalog=http://files.geomajas.org/archetype-latest.xml</programlisting>
          </example>

          <para>Maven will now prompt the user for input.</para>

          <note>
            <para>If anything fails with these maven commands, you need to
            check the output to check the problem. One typical problem is the
            need to define a proxy to allow maven to access sites in the
            outside world. See the <ulink
            url="http://maven.apache.org/guides/mini/guide-proxies.html">http://maven.apache.org/guides/mini/guide-proxies.html</ulink>
            for details.</para>
          </note>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step2</emphasis>: Maven will display the full list
          of available archetypes. Make sure you select the correct one:
          <emphasis role="bold">geomajas-gwt-archetype</emphasis>. In the
          image below, the correct number would be 36:</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Choose the correct archetype</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/select-archetype.png" width="75%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step3</emphasis>: Next maven asks for the <emphasis
          role="bold">groupId</emphasis>. Often the package name is used.
          (foo.bar)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step4</emphasis>: Next maven asks for the <emphasis
          role="bold">artifactId</emphasis>. This represents the name for your
          application. (i.e. my-app)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step5</emphasis>: Next maven asks for the first
          version for your application. 1.0-SNAPSHOT is a good first
          version.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Step6</emphasis>: Next maven asks for the base
          package wherein to place Java files. By default this is the same as
          the groupId. Just hit "enter" to continue.</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Screenshot when building the Geomajas GWT archetype</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/run-archetype.png" width="75%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <tip>
        <para>You have now create a Geomajas template project! It is best to
        continue by testing if everything went well.</para>
      </tip>
    </section>

    <section id="testtempl">
      <title>Testing the template project</title>

      <para>From the project root, you can immediately compile, test (using
      jetty as servlet container), or run the application in development mode
      using the following commands.</para>

      <section id="crefubi">
        <title>Creating a full build</title>

        <para>You now have several options to actually test your application.
        First of all, you could compile it, and create a build. This can be
        done using the following command:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Creating a build from your project</title>

          <para><programlisting>mvn install</programlisting></para>
        </example>

        <para>The "install" target will create a .war file for the project in
        the <code>target</code> directory. This web archive can be dropped
        into a Java application container such as Tomcat.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="runapp">
        <title>Running the compiled template application (full speed)</title>

        <para>Secondly, if you don't have a Java application container ready
        or want a quick test, then you can use mvn to run the application
        for you, using the following commands:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Create a build, then run it</title>

          <para><programlisting>mvn jetty:run</programlisting></para>
        </example>

        <para>The "jetty:run" variant will immediately start a jetty server
        and start the application. This way, you can test your application at
        full speed (as when deployed). The application can be accessed at
        <ulink
        url="http://localhost:8080/">http://localhost:8080/</ulink>.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="rundevapp">
        <title>Running the template application in development mode</title>

        <para>Another option is to start up the application in GWT development
        mode, using the following command lines:</para>

        <example>
          <title>Run the template application in development mode</title>

          <para><programlisting>mvn gwt:run</programlisting></para>
        </example>

        <para>The "gwt:run" option allows you to start the application in GWT
        development mode. A console will appear which allows starting your
        application (from the browser). Amongst other things, this allows you
        to see the messages GWT generates and see the output of the
        "<code>GWT.log</code>" commands.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="eclipse">
    <title>Eclipse</title>

    <para>The combination of Eclipse, maven and GWT is not quite trivial,
    especially for complex multi-module projects like Geomajas. There are 2
    approaches possible for integrating eclipse with maven:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Eclipse plug-in for maven, avoiding the use of the maven
        command-line interface: m2eclipse (<ulink
        url="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/">http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/</ulink>)
        is the most mature project here</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Maven plug-in to generate eclipse project configurations:
        maven-eclipse-plugin (<ulink
        url="http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-eclipse-plugin/">http://maven.apache.org/plugins/maven-eclipse-plugin/</ulink>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>It is clear that an IDE integrated solution like m2eclipse offers
    considerable advantages over manually generating Eclipse project
    configurations:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>direct import of maven projects</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>support for maven properties and filtering</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In-place editing of poms</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>full dependency support</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>For a functional Geomajas setup, the following Eclipse plug-ins
    should be installed on a fresh Galileo download (<ulink
    url="http://www.eclipse.org/downloads/">http://www.eclipse.org/downloads/</ulink>):</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>m2eclipse: update site
        http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/sites/m2e</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>m2eclipse extras (especially WTP extension):
        http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/sites/m2e-extras</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>checkstyle: update site http://eclipse-cs.sf.net/update/</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SVN team provider: update site
        http://download.eclipse.org/releases/helios, choose Collaboration
        -&gt;Subversive SVN Team Provider (Incubation)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Google's GWT Eclipse plug-in:
        http://dl.google.com/eclipse/plugin/3.6 (Plugin and SDK)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section>
      <title>Running/debugging with the Google Plug-in for Eclipse (embedded
      Jetty option)</title>

      <para>There is a classpath issue with the Google Plug-in for Eclipse
      (GPE) that prevents us from using it in a reliable way when there are
      multiple versions of artifacts in the maven dependency tree:<ulink
      url="http://code.google.com/p/google-web-toolkit/issues/detail?id=5033">
      http://code.google.com/p/google-web-toolkit/issues/detail?id=5033</ulink></para>

      <para>On top of that, GPE forces the use of the built-in jetty launcher,
      which has problems with loading libraries from the maven repository.
      Recent development by Google points in the direction of better maven
      support, but a as far as we know a stable solution which does not
      require explicit user interaction is not available. (see <ulink
      url="http://googlewebtoolkit.blogspot.com/2010/08/how-to-use-google-plugin-for-eclipse.html">http://googlewebtoolkit.blogspot.com/2010/08/how-to-use-google-plugin-for-eclipse.html</ulink>).</para>

      <para>In view of these problems, the following workaround seems to be
      the most reliable way of using the GWT plugin for us:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the GWT plug-in with the no-server option (this can be
          done straight from the project since GWT 2.1</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Run an embedded Jetty server to replace the GWT server</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The following series of steps have to be performed to achieve a
      working project.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Import the project as a maven project</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Import project as Maven project</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-wtp-import.png" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>After the project has been imported and the workspace has been
          built, you should now manually mark the project as a GWT project in
          the project properties dialog. Open the Google -&gt; Web Toolkit
          section and mark the checkbox. If the eclipse GWT version differs
          from the project version, the "Use specific SDK" checkbox will be
          enabled:</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Eclipse project properties dialog, Google Web
            Toolkit</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-gwt-modules.png"
                           width="60%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the Google -&gt; Web Application section, the WAR directory
          should be changed to the default maven war sources directory
          (src/main/webapp)<figure>
              <title>Eclipse project properties dialog, Google Web
              Application</title>

              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-gwt-webapp.png"
                             width="70%" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </figure></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Open the debug configurations dialog and create a new Java
          application:</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Debug configurations dialog</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-debug-configurations.png"
                           width="60%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Search for JettyRunner as the main class. JettyRunner is a
          specially prepared main class that starts up Jetty with the correct
          parameters (port 8888 and src/main/webapp as webapp
          directory)</para>

          <figure>
            <title>JettyRunner as main class</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-jetty-runner.png"
                           width="60%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Run the new Jetty server configuration (in debug mode):</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Running Jetty</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-jetty-console.png"
                           width="50%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Now, run the GWT plug-in in no-server mode by by
          right-clicking on the project and selecting Debug As -&gt; Web
          Application (running on an external server):</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Running the GWT application</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-gwt-debug.png" width="70%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Click ok on the dialog screen</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can now add breakpoints and debug your application as if
          it was a normal Java application.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If you have multiple versions of GWT in your project
          workspace, make sure that the gwt-dev jar is in front of the default
          classpath (reported GWT issue):</para>

          <figure>
            <title>Classpath of GWT plug-in (no-server mode)</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-gwt-runner-classpath.png"
                           width="60%" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="eclipwtp">
      <title>Running/debugging with the Google Plug-in for Eclipse</title>

      <para>If you want to run your application directly with GPE, some extra
      actions are needed to avoid classpath problems. You will have to change
      your web.xml by adding a special context listener that allows Spring
      component scanning and circumvents a GeoTools problem with the builtin
      Jetty classloader:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;listener&gt;
 &lt;listener-class&gt;org.geomajas.servlet.PrepareScanningContextListener&lt;/listener-class&gt;
&lt;/listener&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>This solves most of the classpath problems but does not cure the
      problem of having multiple artifact versions in the classpath! This is
      usually only a problem when you have several Geomajas projects opened in
      your workspace. If this is the case, run the GWT plug-in with an
      embedded Jetty server as explained in the previous chapter and you
      should be fine. Note that this should be the first listener in your
      web.xm files, before the spring listeners.</para>

      <para>The following steps are needed to run GPE directly:</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Follow the configuration steps of the indirect mode, right
            up to the Jetty part</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Run the project as a GWT Web application by right-clicking
            on the project and selecting <code>Run as -&gt; Web
            Application</code>.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>For debugging, debug the project as a GWT Web application by
            right-clicking on the project and selecting <code>Debug as -&gt;
            Web Application</code>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="idea">
    <title>IntelliJ IDEA</title>

    <para>The setup in IntelliJ IDEA is quite straightforward and does not
    require running a separate Maven command. Just open the project from IDEA
    by selecting the pom in the root directory.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Open project using pom</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/IDEA-open-project.png" width="50%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>IDEA will recognize this as a GWT project and assign the correct
    facet but as always you will have to make your own run configuration
    (which is fortunately trivial). You will need version 9.0 or later for the
    GWT 2.0 support.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>IDEA GWT run configuration</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/IDEA-run-configuration.png" width="90%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Before being able to use this configuration, you need to invoke the
    gwt:i18n Maven target to assure the files which are used for
    internationalisation are available (otherwise, you will get compilation
    errors). You can do this from the "Maven projects" tab.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>run gwt:i18 target</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/IDEA-maven-targets.png" width="60%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Some additional settings have to be done in the "project structure"
    dialog. Apart from specifying the GWT installation directory, there is a
    specific project setting which has to be done manually, which is setting
    the target Web facet to "Web". The project structure for the simple GWT
    project should look as follows:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Project structure for simple GWT project</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/IDEA-project-structure.png" width="80%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>After this, you should be able to run the project. Any changes in
    the source code will be automatically detected, and debugging is
    possible.</para>

    <note>
      <para>When creating GWT run configurations, it is recommended to
      increase the amount of memory given to the process. You can do this by
      entering a higher -Xmx value in the VM parameters field, for example
      "-Xmx768m".</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="netbeans">
    <title>NetBeans</title>

    <para>You can both create the project from the archetype or open directly
    the Maven project in NetBeans. See <ulink
    url="http://wiki.netbeans.org/MavenBestPractices">http://wiki.netbeans.org/MavenBestPractices</ulink>
    for more details.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using a Hibernate layer</title>

    <para>The template project can easily be modified to use a layer stored in
    PostGIS. You should do the following;</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>In the pom.xml, uncomment block marked with "uncomment if you
          want to use Hibernate with postgis, for another db you will need
          similar dependencies".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the web.xml file (src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml)
          uncomment the block marked with "To use Roads layer stored in
          PostGIS through hibernate layer, uncomment the following".</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>To create the database, you can use the following command
    which will create the database (named "app") with some sample data (just a
    couple of roads):</para>

    <para><programlisting>psql -d app &lt;src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/example/road.sql</programlisting></para>
  </section>

  <section id="cont">
    <title>How to continue</title>

    <para>The archetype generates a dependency on the geomajas-dep project to
    manage the version of the Geomajas dependencies. This project exists for
    the sole purpose of keeping track of the latest released versions. It is
    quite likely that a new version of geomajas-dep has been released since
    the latest release of the archetype. Therefore, we recommend you update
    this dependency to the latest version. You can check the latest version
    using this URL: <ulink
    url="http://repo.geomajas.org/nexus/index.html#nexus-search;quick~geomajas-dep">http://repo.geomajas.org/nexus/index.html#nexus-search;quick~geomajas-dep</ulink>.</para>

    <para>The most important configuration files in the project are the
    following:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>main configuration :
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/applicationContext.xml</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>map configuration :
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/mapMain.xml</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>overview map configuration:
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/mapOverview.xml</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>countries layer configuration :
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/clientLayerCountries.xml</code> and
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/layerCountries.xml</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>OpenStreetMap layer configuration :
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/clientLayerOsm.xml</code> and
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/layerOsm.xml</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>GWT configuration file :
          <code>src/main/java/Application.gwt.xml</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>web.xml:
          <code>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/WEB-INF/web.xml</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>More details about the Geomajas configuration are found
    in the <ulink
    url="http://files.geomajas.org/maven/trunk/geomajas/docbook-devuserguide/html/master.html#part-configuration">developer's
    guide</ulink>.</para>

    <para>Reference which may be interesting to read:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>GWT project page: <ulink
          url="http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/">http://code.google.com/webtoolkit/</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>SmartGWT showcase: <ulink
          url="http://www.smartclient.com/smartgwt/showcase/">http://www.smartclient.com/smartgwt/showcase/</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DZone's GWT refcardz: <ulink
          url="http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/gwt-style-configuration-and-js">http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/gwt-style-configuration-and-js</ulink>.</para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>spring documentation: <ulink
          url="http://www.springsource.org/documentation">http://www.springsource.org/documentation</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DZone's spring configuration refcardz: <ulink
          url="http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/spring-configuration">http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/spring-configuration</ulink>.</para>

          <para></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>maven project: <ulink
          url="http://maven.apache.org/">http://maven.apache.org/</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Maven by example book: <ulink
          url="http://www.sonatype.com/books/mvnex-book/reference/public-book.html">http://www.sonatype.com/books/mvnex-book/reference/public-book.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>maven reference book: <ulink
          url="http://www.sonatype.com/books/mvnref-book/reference/public-book.html">http://www.sonatype.com/books/mvnref-book/reference/public-book.html</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DZone's maven 2 refcardz: <ulink
          url="http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/apache-maven-2">http://refcardz.dzone.com/refcardz/apache-maven-2</ulink>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section>
</chapter>
