<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="ch-arch">
  <title>GWT face architecture</title>

  <section id="comm">
    <title>Client-server communication</title>

    <para>Client-server communication in Geomajas is executed through a series
    of commands instantiated on the client and executed by the server. In the
    GWT face, all such commands are executed by
    <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.command.GwtCommandDispatcher</code>. This
    class has one single method for instantiating such commands and handling
    the result: the <code>execute</code> method.</para>

    <para>The command object, required by the execute method
    (<code>GwtCommand</code>), is in fact a wrapper around a
    <code>CommandRequest</code> object (see <link
    linkend="architecture-command">architecture</link>), wherein the name of
    the requested command is found. Each command expects a certain
    implementation of the <code>CommandRequest</code> and
    <code>CommandResponse</code> objects. Note that these request and response
    objects must also be known server-side, and thus will not be packaged
    within the GWT client packages. As additional parameters for the execute
    method, <code>CommandCallback</code> objects can be passed. These can
    contain methods to call after successful or unsuccessful completion of the
    command. It is recommended to extend AbstractCommandCallback for your
    implementation.</para>

    <para>The GwtCommandDispatcher is also the central access point for
    security in the GWT face. You should register a TokenRequestHandler to
    handle the login procedure if needed. You can read data about the current
    user when logged in.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Note that insufficient authorizations can be difficult to debug.
      When no commands can be executed on the server, the logging on the
      server also fails. When logging in is done using a command, execution of
      that command needs to be allowed. Failure the configure the system to
      have minimal authorizations will likely cause your map to be invisible
      without any feedback.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="mapsmodel">
    <title>The map's model</title>

    <para>As with any GIS framework or application, the most crucial of all
    entities is the Map. A map is represented by the
    <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.widget.<code>MapWidget</code></code>, but is
    set up using the standard model-view-controller paradigm. The widget is
    the actual view of a map, with <code>Painter</code> objects building the
    display. The user interaction is handled using controllers, represented by
    the <code>GraphicsController</code> interface. The third aspect, the
    model, is represented by the
    <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.<code>MapModel</code></code>.</para>

    <section id="MapModel">
      <title>MapModel</title>

      <para>The definition of the model behind a map
      (<code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.<code>MapModel</code></code>). This
      object stores all map metadata and layers, and has an extensive arsenal
      of methods to operate on the layers and the features.</para>

      <para>Another aspect of the <code>MapModel</code> is the list of events
      that it fires. Handlers for the following events can be added to the
      <code>MapModel</code>:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>MapModelEvent</emphasis>: this event is fired when
          the <code>MapModel</code> has been properly initialized. When a
          <code>MapWidget</code> is added to the HTML page, it automatically
          triggers an initialization method. This will ask the server to
          supply it with the correct metadata, so that the
          <code>MapModel</code> can actually build it's layers, etc. Once this
          initialization process is done, a <code>MapModelEvent</code> will be
          fired. Add a
          <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.event.MapModelHandler</code> to
          use this.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>FeatureSelectedEvent</emphasis>: this event is fired
          every time a feature within one of this model's vector layers is
          selected. Add a
          <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.event.FeatureSelectionHandler</code>
          to use this.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>FeatureDeselectedEvent</emphasis>: this event is
          fired every time a feature within one of this model's vector layers
          is deselected. Add a
          <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.event.FeatureSelectionHandler</code>
          to use this.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>LayerSelectedEvent</emphasis>: this event is fired
          every time a layer within this model is selected. Add a
          <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.event.LayerSelectionHandler</code>
          to use this.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>LayerDeselectedEvent</emphasis>: this event is fired
          every time a layer within this model is deselected. Add a
          <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.event.LayerSelectionHandler</code>
          to use this.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="MapView">
      <title>MapView</title>

      <para>Part of a map is this
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.MapView</code> object, which
      determines and influences what area is currently visible. Internally the
      <code>MapView</code> has a <code>Camera</code> object that you can think
      of a a satellite that floats above the map. This <code>Camera</code>
      floats at a certain height, on a certain position, and this will
      determine what part of the map is shown.</para>

      <para>The map contains several coordinate spaces.</para>

      <para><itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>world space : coordinates use the crs of the map.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>screen space : pixel coordinates.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>pan space : objects have already been scaled to the map's
            current scale, but the translation transformation still needs to
            occur. This is space is used for rendering the layers and should
            normally not be used for other purposes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>The <code>MapView</code> provides conversions of
      coordinates between these spaces. Inside the MapView is a transformer
      (<code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.spatial.WorldViewTransformer</code>) that
      is able to transform coordinates, geometries and bounding boxes from
      screen space to world space and back.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="WorkFlow">
      <title>Workflow</title>

      <para>A work flow in the GWT face determines how editing should be
      handled. It can consist of several steps, called activities. When a work
      flow finishes, changes will typically be persisted. The package is:
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.map.workflow</code></para>

      <figure>
        <title>Workflow API</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/gwtface_workflow.png"
                       width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Activity:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>execute</emphasis>: this method is called by the
          encompassing processor to execute the activity.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>getErrorHandler</emphasis>: get the error handler
          that is specifically tuned for the activity.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">WorkflowErrorHandler:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>handleError</emphasis>: Executed when an activity
          throws an exception during execution. The
          <code>WorkflowProcessor</code> must make sure this method is
          executed.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">WorkflowContext:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>stopProcess</emphasis>: informs the
          <code>WorkflowProcessor</code> to stop the processing of activities.
          It is the <code>WorkflowProcessors</code> responsibility to ask for
          this, and execute no more activities when "<code>true</code>" is
          returned.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>setSeedData</emphasis>: provide some seed
          information to the context. This is usually provided at the time of
          work flow kickoff.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">WorkflowProcessor:</emphasis></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>supports</emphasis>: ensure that each activity
          configured in this process is supported. This method should be
          called by implemented subclasses for each activity that is part of
          the process.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>doActivities</emphasis>: this method kicks off the
          processing of work flow activities.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>setActivities</emphasis>: set a list of activities
          to be executed in the process. This would also be a good time to
          check if activities are supported.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>setDefaultErrorHandler</emphasis>: set a default
          error handler, which is invoked when the activity throws an uncaught
          exception.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="selfeat">
      <title>Selection of features</title>

      <para>A feature in a vector layer has the possibility to be selected.
      Selection usually changes the colour of the feature on the map or in a
      table to make it stand out. The actual selecting handled by the
      <code>MapModel</code>. In the map model, the selected features are
      stored. After all, it is possible that by moving away from a certain
      area, the selected features are no longer in sight, and perhaps no
      longer in the client layer-cache. Still their contents may be needed for
      specific tasks.</para>

      <para>The <code>MapModel</code> fires events when changes in selection
      occur. It will fire either <code>FeatureSelectedEvent</code> or
      <code>FeatureDeselectedEvent</code>. The <code>MapModel</code>
      implements the <code>HasFeatureSelectionHandler</code> interface so
      other components can register with the <code>MapModel</code> as
      <code>FeatureSelectionHandler</code>. For example the
      <code>MapWidget</code> will register itself as a handler to know when a
      feature is selected or deselected and redraw it accordingly.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Selection events and handlers</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/gwtface_selection.png"
                       width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When writing code that needs to react upon the selection of
      features, implement the <code>FeatureSelectionHandler</code> interface,
      and register yourself with the <code>MapModel</code>.</para>

      <para><note>
          <para>Individual vector layers can also fire selection events.
          Actually the <code>MapModel</code> propagates the events from the
          individual vector layers, so that the user need only install his
          handlers in one place.</para>
        </note></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="spatial">
    <title>The spatial package</title>

    <para>The spatial package (<code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.spatial</code>)
    contains a collection of math and geometry related classes and utilities
    to provide all the client-side calculations one should need. If really
    complex calculations need to be performed, it's best to let the server
    (probably using JTS) handle it anyway. The root of the package contains
    the general mathematical definitions of a Vector, Matrix, LineSegment, and
    so on. It also provides a general math library and the
    <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.spatial.WorldViewTransformer</code>.</para>

    <para>The <code>WorldViewTransformer</code> in particular can be a very
    valuable tool. It allows you to transform coordinates, bounding boxes and
    geometries between the 3 pre-defined spaces (world, view, pan).</para>

    <section id="geom">
      <title>Geometry definitions</title>

      <para>All <code>Geometry</code> definitions in the GWT face are based on
      geometries from JTS, the Java Topology Suite, and the OGC simple feature
      specification. The classes can be found in the
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.spatial.geometry</code> package. Supported
      geometries are:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>Point</code>: a geometry representation of a single
          coordinate.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>MultiPoint</code>: a geometry containing multiple
          <code>Point</code> geometries.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>LineString</code>: a list of connected coordinates.
          Sometimes also called a polyline.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>LinearRing</code>: an extension of the
          <code>LineString</code> geometry that expects the last coordinate to
          be equal to the first coordinate. In other words, a
          <code>LinearRing</code> is a closed <code>LineString</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>MultiLineString</code>: a geometry containing multiple
          <code>LineString</code> geometries.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>Polygon</code>: a <code>Polygon</code> is a two-part
          geometry, consisting of an exterior <code>LinearRing</code> and a
          list of interior <code>LinearRings</code>. The exterior
          <code>LinearRing</code>, also called the shell, is the outer hull of
          the geometry, while the interior rings can be seen as holes in the
          exterior ring's surface area.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>MultiPolygon</code>: a geometry containing multiple
          <code>Polygon</code> geometries.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="editgeom">
      <title>Editing geometries</title>

      <para>The <code>Geometry</code> implementations themselves do not have
      any setters methods. Instead the editing of geometries is done through a
      series of operations, all implementing the <code>
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.spatial.geometry.operation.GeometryOperation</code>
      </code> interface. This interface consists of only one method, accepting
      a geometry, and returning the result as a new geometry.</para>

      <para>Geometries have no public constructors, so the creation of new
      geometries is done using a factory,
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.spatial.geometry.GeometryFactory</code>. A
      <code>GeometryFactory</code> can be created using a spatial reference id
      and a certain precision, but it can also be retrieved from any geometry
      instance (where srid and precision are automatically correct).</para>

      <para><code>GeometryOperation</code> interface:</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/GeometryOperation.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="snapping">
      <title>Snapping</title>

      <para>Snapping in Geomajas, is handled by a single manager class called
      the <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.spatial.snapping.Snapper</code>. It is
      the main handler for snapping to coordinates. It supports different
      modes of operation and different algorithms for the actual snapping. The
      different algorithms to use are defined in the vector layer
      configuration files, while the modes are defined by the different
      implementations of the <code>SnappingMode</code> class. Let us first
      start with the different modes:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ALL_GEOMETRIES_EQUAL</emphasis>: this snapping mode
          considers all geometries equal when it comes to determining where to
          snap to. Depending on the snapping algorithm used, it will consider
          all nearby geometries.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>PRIORITY_TO_INTERSECTING_GEOMETRIES</emphasis>: this
          snapping mode tries to snap to intersecting geometries before trying
          the general approach. When searching a snapping coordinate for a
          given point, this mode will first search for intersecting geometries
          and try to get a snap to that. If no snapping point can be found, it
          will consider all nearby geometries (like
          ALL_GEOMETRIES_EQUAL).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The snapping rules themselves are defined in the server-side
      configuration. Each vector layer can have many snapping rules. For each
      rule, 3 fields must be filled:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>layer</emphasis>: the target layer to snap
          to.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>distance</emphasis>: the distance over which to
          snap. This distance must be expressed in the map's coordinate
          system.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>type</emphasis>: the snapping algorithm to use. At
          the moment 2 types of snapping algorithms are supported: to the
          nearest point (type=1), and to the nearest edge (type=2). For
          nearest point snapping can only occur to any coordinate which is a
          end-point for a geometry, for nearest edge that can be any
          coordinate on the edge of the geometry. Needless to say, the nearest
          edge requires more calculating power than the nearest point.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">Snapping on the map</emphasis></para>

      <para>When a <code>GraphicsController</code> for the map needs to use
      snapping (i.e. editing controllers), they should extend the
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.controller.AbstractSnappingController</code>
      class. This class extends the <code>GraphicsController</code> class (the
      base class for all Geomajas map controllers), and overwrites the
      <code>getScreenPosition</code> and <code>getWorldPosition</code> methods
      to assure the points are snapped. The
      <code>AbstractSnappingController</code> also supports the on-the-fly
      activation and deactivation of snapping.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="graphrend">
    <title id="graphics">Graphics &amp; rendering</title>

    <para>In the GWT face, the main <code>render</code> method can be found in
    <code>MapWidget</code>. The render method requires three parameters, a
    paintable object, a target group to paint in and a status. The paintable
    object is the actual object that needs to be painted. The target group
    (<code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.widget.MapWidget.RenderGroup</code>)
    specifies where in the DOM to draw. The usual choices here are the SCREEN
    or the WORLD groups. The rendering status
    (<code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.widget.MapWidget.RenderStatus</code>)
    determines what drawing action to take.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">RenderStatus</emphasis></para>

    <para>The render status can be one of the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>ALL</emphasis>: completely render or re-render the
        paintable object. If the paintable object contains other paintable
        object, go through them recursively (a map will paint layers, who in
        turn will paint tiles,...)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>UPDATE</emphasis>: update the paintable object in
        question, but do not update recursively.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>DELETE</emphasis>: delete the paintable object from
        the map.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>While rendering, the map uses a visitor to visit the paintable
    objects recursively and search for painters for each object or sub-object.
    The "ALL" status will paint recursively while the "UPDATE" status will not
    go deeper then the given paintable object. Of course, if a given paintable
    object has no recursive paintable objects, then the difference between
    "ALL" and "UPDATE" is irrelevant.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">RenderGroup</emphasis></para>

    <para>The render group that needs to be specified when calling the map's
    render method, represents the logical place on the map to draw the
    paintable object. There are four choices, each having a huge
    impact.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>WORLD</emphasis>: drawing should be done in world
        coordinates. World coordinates means that the map coordinate system
        should be used. The advantage of rendering objects in the world group,
        is that when the user moves the map around, the objects will move with
        it.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>SCREEN</emphasis>: drawing should be done in screen
        coordinates. Screen coordinates are expressed in pixels, starting from
        the top left corner of the map. When rendering objects in the screen
        group they will always appear at a fixed position, even when the user
        moves the map about.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>RASTER</emphasis>: drawing should be done in pan
        coordinates. All raster layers are drawn in this group. In essence
        this means that the coordinates are expected to have been scaled for
        the current scale before drawing, and that only the translation still
        needs to occur. For advanced use only.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>VECTOR</emphasis>: drawing should be done in pan
        coordinates. All vector layers, their selection and their labels are
        drawn in this group. In essence this means that the coordinates are
        expected to have been scaled for the current scale before drawing, and
        that only the translation still needs to occur. For advanced use
        only.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section id="gfx">
      <title>GFX interfaces</title>

      <para>As will be explained in more detail in the "rendering manual",
      there are 2 ways of drawing on the map: directly using some rendering
      context, or indirectly using <code>Paintable</code> objects,
      <code>Painter</code>s and the <code>MapWidget</code>'s
      <code>render</code> method (as explained above). When using the direct
      approach, one has to call the methods of one of the different rendering
      contexts. A <code>MapWidget</code> contains a <code>MapContext</code>
      implementation, which in turn contains 3 different contexts:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>MenuContext</emphasis>: used for keeping details
          about right mouse clicks. Not used for rendering.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ImageContext</emphasis>: used for rendering images
          in HTML. All raster layers use this context.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>GraphicsContext</emphasis>: the main vector graphics
          renderer. Can also render images, but uses SVG or VML to do so. When
          rendering shapes, circles, rectangle, etc. you will always be using
          this context.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <figure>
        <title>Main context interfaces from the GFX package</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/gwtface_gfx_context.png"
                       width="" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The <code>GraphicsContext</code> is the main vector drawing
      context. It has two implementations: one for SVG and one for VML.</para>

      <figure id="graphicscontext">
        <title>GraphicsContext interface</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center"
                       fileref="images/gwtface_graphicscontext.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Every object that appears on a Geomajas map, has to implement the
      <code>Paintable</code> interface. This interface marks types of objects
      that can be painted. For each type/class of paintable object, an
      accompanying <code>Painter</code> must be defined as well. The painter
      will ultimately decide exactly how a paintable object should be
      rendered. The painter will render objects using it's <code>paint</code>
      method, or delete objects from the map using it's
      <code>deleteShape</code> method.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>General graphics interfaces</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="images/gwtface_gfx.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>GraphicsContext</emphasis>: this is the basic
          drawing interface. Different implementations will draw in different
          technologies (i.e. <code>SvgGraphicsContext</code> and
          <code>VmlGraphicsContext</code>). The whole idea of this
          <code>GraphicsContext</code> and the painters, was inspired by the
          Java AWT library. This context will draw basic shapes, according to
          their id. Since we are using web technologies, all implementations
          (be they SVG or VML) will use DOM elements to create their
          drawings.</para>

          <para>There are two different kinds of DOM elements we like to
          distinguish: group elements and non-group elements.</para>

          <para><emphasis>Group elements</emphasis> are container elements
          that have no particular representation of themselves but are used to
          group other elements and create hierarchical dependency. In SVG,
          they are represented by <code>&lt;g&gt;</code> tags, in VML these
          are <code>&lt;group&gt;</code> tags. <emphasis>Group elements or
          groups </emphasis>can be drawn by passing an arbitrary Java object
          to the <code>drawGroup()</code>method. This object can be used for
          later reference to the group. To position the group in the
          hierarchy, a parent group object can be passed as a second parameter
          to the <code>drawGroup()</code> method.</para>

          <para><emphasis>Non-group elements</emphasis> (all other elements
          like circle, rectangle, symbol, etc.) can be drawn by passing a
          group element - the parent - and a name to the element-specific
          drawing method (<code>drawCircle()</code>,
          <code>drawRectangle()</code>, etc.). These elements will be attached
          to their parent group in the DOM. Each non-group element in the
          <code>GraphicsContext</code> DOM tree will therefore have a name and
          a parent group object. This combination of name and parent can later
          be used to update or delete the object.</para>

          <para>In essence, the drawing methods will result in changes in the
          visuals of the map, and the painters that will call these
          methods.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Paintable</emphasis>: the basic definition of an
          object that can be painted onto the map. For each
          <code>Paintable</code> class, an accompanying <code>Painter</code>
          class must be defined. The <code>Paintable</code> interface has only
          two methods. The <code>getId</code> method returns the
          <code>Paintable</code> objects id, which is it's key in the DOM tree
          within the parent group. While the accept method will be traversed
          by the <code>PainterVisitor</code>, and is used to have the object
          passed to the correct <code>Painter</code>, which will draw the
          object.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>WorldPaintable</emphasis>: extension of the
          <code>Paintable</code> interface for objects that support being
          rendered in world space. This means that it should be possible to
          transform the object's geometry/location/coordinate/bbox.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Painter</emphasis>: A <code>Painter</code> knows how
          to paint a specific kind of <code>Paintable</code> object. Exactly
          what class of <code>Paintable</code> objects it can draw, must be
          made clear by it's <code>getPaintableClassName</code> method.
          Furthermore, the <code>Painter</code> has two methods to paint or
          remove <code>Paintable</code> objects on or from the given
          <code>GraphicsContext</code>. Basically, the <code>Painter</code>
          translates the fields and parameters of the <code>Paintable</code>
          object into calls to the <code>GraphicsContext</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>PainterVisitor</emphasis>: Geomajas uses a visitor
          algorithm for it's client side rendering process. The
          <code>MapWidget</code> uses a <code>PainterVisitor</code> to
          recursively traverse the tree of <code>Paintable</code> objects,
          calling the <code>accept</code> method on each node.</para>

          <para>Of course this recursive system of searching for the correct
          <code>Painter</code>, can only work when the
          <code>PainterVisitor</code> has all the necessary painters
          registered. When registering a <code>Painter</code> with the
          <code>MapWidget</code>, it will actually pass it along to this
          <code>PainterVisitor</code> instance.</para>

          <para>An example of the recursive painting, can be found in the
          <code>MapModel</code>, which calls the <code>accept</code> methods
          of it's layers, which call the <code>accept</code> methods of the
          visible tiles, which contain features.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="rendering">
      <title>Rendering manual</title>

      <para>There are two ways to render objects onto the map. One uses
      <code>Paintable</code> objects and <code>Painter</code>s, the other is
      by using the <code>GraphicsContext</code> directly. There are still some
      general notions that one must know before attempting to draw on the map.
      Since HTML, SVG and VML are all markup languages which use a DOM tree as
      basic model, rendering basically is the adding and removing of nodes
      within this tree. As parent nodes have styling information or other
      attributes that reflect their child nodes, it is very important to add
      nodes to the correct parent when drawing.</para>

      <para>The <link linkend="graphicscontext">GraphicsContext</link>
      reflects this, by requiring a parent object as first parameters in all
      drawing methods. Associated with every node is an object that represents
      it. Given this object, the <code>GraphicsContext</code> can find the
      correct node. When using the <code>GraphicsContext</code> directly, it
      is important to be aware of the necessity of using the correct parent
      group when drawing.</para>

      <section id="rendindi">
        <title>The simple approach - indirect drawing</title>

        <section id="drawscreenspace">
          <title>Drawing in screen space</title>

          <para>This approach uses <code>MapWidget</code>'s render method,
          which requires three parameters: a <code>Paintable</code> object, a
          target <code>RenderGroup</code>, and a <code>RenderStatus</code>. If
          you are unfamiliar with these, visit the <link
          linkend="graphics">beginning of this chapter</link> for a detailed
          description.</para>

          <para>Let us start with an example, where we draw a rectangle in
          screen space (=pixel coordinates). The code would look something
          like this:</para>

          <programlisting>Rectangle rectangle = new Rectangle("myRectangle");
rectangle.setBounds(new Bbox(10, 10, 200, 200));
rectangle.setStyle(new ShapeStyle("#FF0000", .8f, "#0000FF", .6f, 2));

map.render(rectangle, RenderGroup.SCREEN, RenderStatus.ALL);</programlisting>

          <para>This code snippet would draw a rectangle (which implements
          <code>Paintable</code>), called "myRectangle" in screen space (10
          pixels from the top, 10 pixels from the left, and with a width and
          height of both 200), using the defined style (red interior with a
          blue border). To delete the rectangle again, you would have to do
          something like this:</para>

          <programlisting>map.render(rectangle, RenderGroup.SCREEN, RenderStatus.DELETE);</programlisting>
        </section>

        <section id="renddrawworldspace">
          <title>Drawing in world space</title>

          <para>Remember that there was also an extension of the
          <code><code>Paintable</code></code> interface, designed for
          rendering objects in world space. Rendering in world space means
          that objects are drawn in the coordinate system of the map. This
          also means that when the user moves about on the map, the object
          will move with it (keeping the same location in map coordinates).
          Only objects that implement the <code>WorldPaintable</code>
          interface can be drawn in world space.</para>

          <para>Let us, for the next example, assume that the map has been
          defined using EPSG:4326 (lonlat) as coordinate system, and we would
          apply the following code snippet:</para>

          <programlisting>Rectangle rectangle = new Rectangle("myRectangle");
rectangle.setBounds(new Bbox(-60, -60, 120, 120));
rectangle.setStyle(new ShapeStyle("#FF0000", .8f, "#0000FF", .6f, 2));

// Register the rectangle to the map, so that it gets redrawn
// automatically when the user navigates on the map.
map.registerWorldPaintable(rectangle);</programlisting>

          <para>Starting from -60, -60 and using a width and height of 120, we
          would have a rectangle that encompasses a huge part of the world.
          Note that drawing objects in world space requires you to register
          them with the map. This is necessary to have the map automatically
          update the object's position when the user navigates. When
          registering the <code>WorldPaintable</code> rectangle, it is
          automatically drawn on the map.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section id="useGraphicsContext">
        <title>The advanced approach - using the GraphicsContext
        directly</title>

        <para>When more flexibility is required from the rendering system, the
        map's render method might sometimes not be enough. If for example we
        want to render more than one object within a specific parent group.
        The following code snippet shows how to render a specific parent in
        screen space and then render a circle within this parent group:</para>

        <programlisting>// Create a parent group within screen space:
Composite parent = new Composite("myParent");
map.getVectorContext().drawGroup(map.getGroup(RenderGroup.SCREEN), parent);

// Draw a circle at (20, 20) with radius 10 pixels within parent group:
Coordinate pos = new Coordinate(20, 20);
ShapeStyle style = new ShapeStyle("#FF0000", .8f, "#0000FF", .6f, 2);
map.getVectorContext().drawCircle(parent, "myCircle", pos, 10, style);</programlisting>

        <para>Since no special parameters are added to the "myParent" node,
        the circle is drawn as if it were in the screen group itself. But
        thanks to the extra parent group, we now have the ability for apply
        specific styling or transformations on that parent group, and thus
        altering all children within it. Let us for example move the circle
        100 pixels to the right:</para>

        <programlisting>// Translate the parent group 100 pixels to the right:
Matrix m = new Matrix(1, 0, 0, 1, 100, 0);
map.getVectorContext().drawGroup(map.getGroup(RenderGroup.SCREEN), parent, m);</programlisting>

        <warning>
          <para>Do not try to render objects in world space by directly
          accessing the <code>GraphicsContext</code>. Behind the screens of
          the <code>MapWidget</code>, the world space objects are actually
          transformed and rendered in <emphasis>vector</emphasis> space. This
          is done to avoid scaling in the DOM tree (as this is not possible
          cross browsers).</para>
        </warning>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="userInteraction">
    <title id="interaction">User interaction</title>

    <para>This section covers the many interfaces regarding buttons, menu
    items and such that make up the user interface. The specific Geomajas
    widgets (i.e. <code>LayerTree</code>) require a specific way of doing
    things. We will cover the interfaces for the <code>Toolbar</code>,
    <code>LayerTree</code>, map controllers and context menus.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Toolbar</emphasis>: the tool bar has two types of
        default actions one can add to it (there is always the
        <code>addChild</code> method, which can add any widget, but we are now
        talking about Geomajas specific possibilities): the
        <code>ToolbarAction</code> and the <code>ToolbarModalAction</code>.
        The <code>ToolbarAction</code> is used for actions that need immediate
        response upon clicking, while the <code>ToolbarModalAction</code> is
        used for enabling or disabling a certain state.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>LayerTree</emphasis>: the <code>LayerTree</code> has
        the possibility to add buttons to it's tool bar that usually act upon
        the selected layer within the <code>LayerTree</code>. Again two types
        of actions can be added: the <code>LayerTreeAction</code> and the
        <code>LayerTreeModalAction</code>. The same difference as with the
        tool bar applies: the <code>LayerTreeAction</code> is a base abstract
        class for actions that execute immediately upon clicking, while the
        <code>LayerTreeModalAction</code> is used for enabling or disabling a
        certain state (for example: toggle the layer's visibility).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Menu</emphasis>: each item in a context menu should
        extend the <code>MenuAction</code> base class. This is your basic
        starting point for easily creating new menu items or context menu
        items.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>Controllers on the map</emphasis>: for controllers
        listening to mouse events on a map, there is the
        <code>GraphicsController</code> interface, or an abstraction under the
        name of <code>AbstractGraphicsController</code>.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <note>
      <para>For buttons in the <code>Toolbar</code> or <code>LayerTree</code>
      it is possible to add them to the
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.action.toolbar.ToolbarRegistry</code> or
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.action.layertree.LayerTreeRegistry</code>
      upon application startup (before <code>MapWidget</code>
      initialisation!). This allows you to add new buttons which can be
      included in the map configuration.</para>
    </note>

    <section id="tbToolbarAction">
      <title>Toolbar: ToolbarAction</title>

      <para>The <code>ToolbarAction</code> is your basic abstract class for
      building tool bar buttons that are executed immediately when clicked.
      The class implements the <code>ClickHandler</code> interface and
      requires your to specify an icon and a tool tip on creation.</para>

      <para><code>ToolbarAction</code> classes need to be registered in the
      <code> <code>ToolbarRegistry</code> </code> class. This allows you to
      get an instance of the widget to put in the tool bar. The tools which
      are part of the GWT face are statically defined in the class. Other
      tools can be added (or overwritten) at runtime before the map is
      initialised.</para>

      <para>When a <code>ToolbarAction</code> is configurable (XML
      configuration), it should implement the <code>ConfigurableAction</code>
      interface. This contains a "<code>configure()</code>" method which will
      be called for each of the parameters which are defined in the tool
      configuration.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/ToolbarAction.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="tbToolbarModalAction">
      <title>Toolbar: ToolbarModalAction</title>

      <para>The <code>ToolbarModalAction</code> is the basic template for
      creating selectable tool bar buttons. Usually they enable and disable a
      certain state on the map when selected or deselected. Many of the
      implementations that come with Geomajas set a new controller on the map
      when they are selected.</para>

      <para>Note that only one of these <code>ToolbarModalActions</code> can
      be selected at any given time. In that sense they act as radio
      buttons.</para>

      <para><code>ToolbarModalAction</code> classes need to be registered in
      the <code> <code>ToolbarRegistry</code> </code> class. This allows you
      to get an instance of the widget to put in the tool bar. The tools which
      are always part of the GWT face are statically defined in the class.
      Other tools can be added (or overwritten) at runtime before the map is
      initialised.</para>

      <para>When a <code>ToolbarAction</code> is configurable, it should
      implement the <code>ConfigurableAction</code> interface. This contains a
      <code>configure()</code> method which will be called for each of the
      parameters which are defined in the tool configuration.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/ToolbarModalAction.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="ltLayerTreeAction">
      <title>LayerTree: LayerTreeAction</title>

      <para>The <code>LayerTreeAction</code> is your basic abstract class for
      building layer tree buttons that are executed immediately when clicked.
      The <code>onClick()</code> method needs to be implemented and it also
      requires you to specify an icon, a tool tip and a disabled icon. Note
      that the <code>onClick()</code> has the selected layer within the
      <code>LayerTree</code> as a parameter.</para>

      <para><code>LayerTreeAction</code> classes need to be registered in the
      <code>LayerTreeRegistry</code> class. The tools which are always part of
      the GWT face are statically defined in the class. Other tools can be
      added (or overwritten) at runtime before the map is initialised.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/LayerTreeAction.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="ltLayerTreeModalAction">
      <title>LayerTree: LayerTreeModalAction</title>

      <para>The <code>LayerTreeModalAction</code> is the basic template for
      creating selectable layer tree buttons. Usually they enable and disable
      a certain state for the selected layer within the layer tree (for
      example that layer's visibility).</para>

      <para><code>LayerTreeModalAction</code> classes need to be registered in
      the <code>LayerTreeRegistry</code> class. The tools which are always
      part of the GWT face are statically defined in the class. Other tools
      can be added (or overwritten) at runtime before the map is
      initialised.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="mMenuAction">
      <title>Menu: MenuAction</title>

      <para>To create menu items or context menu items, Geomajas provides a
      base which extends from SmartGWT's <code>MenuItem</code> class. It
      requires you to set a title and icon. It also implements the
      <code>ClickHandler</code> interface for defining the
      <code>onClick()</code> execution function.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/MenuAction.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="mapControllers">
      <title>Controllers on the map</title>

      <section id="cGraphicsController">
        <title>GraphicsController</title>

        <para>For interactive mouse controllers on the map there is a general
        interface, <code>GraphicsController</code>. To write a custom
        controller, you should always extend
        <code>AbstractGraphicsController</code>.</para>

        <caution>
          <para>The <code>GraphicsController</code> interface does NOT use
          SmartGWT events as they provide no way of getting the target DOM
          element from the mouse events. So the list of handlers that the
          <code>GraphicsController</code> extends, are all basic GWT event
          handlers. A separate widget (<code>GraphicsWidget</code>) has been
          created to catch the events, while the normal <code>MapWidget</code>
          (which encapsulates the <code>GraphicsWidget</code>) can still
          handle SmartGWT events.</para>
        </caution>

        <para>On top of all the event handling methods that come from the
        different handlers, the interface also has <code>onActivate()</code>
        and an <code>onDeactivate()</code> methods. The
        <code>onActivate()</code> is called before the controller is actually
        applied on the <code>GraphicsWidget</code>. This is usually used to
        apply a new context menu on the map and such. The
        <code>onDeactivate()</code> method is called when the controller is
        removed from the <code>GraphicsWidget</code>. This is usually used for
        cleaning up.</para>

        <xi:include href="listing/GraphicsController.xml"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

        <para>You should never directly implement
        <code>GraphicsController</code> (not that it does not have the
        "<code>@UserImplemented</code>" annotation), you should always extend
        <code>AbstractGraphicsController</code>. This abstract class
        implements all methods as empty methods so you don't have to clutter
        your code with empty methods (often only a few of the mouse event
        methods are actually used). It also has some extra methods for return
        useful information for the mouse events, such as the position
        (expressed in screen coordinates) or the target DOM element.</para>

        <para>Small extract from the <code>AbstractGraphicsController</code>
        class:</para>

        <xi:include href="listing/AbstractGraphicsController.xml"
                    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

        <para>Now that you have your controller you can set it;</para>

        <programlisting>mapWidget.setController(new MeasureDistanceController(mapWidget));</programlisting>

        <note>
          <para>There are more abstractions than just the
          <code>AbstractGraphicsController</code>:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <code>AbstractRectangleController</code>
              </emphasis>: abstract controller that handles drawing a
              rectangle by dragging the mouse on the map.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis> <code>AbstractSnappingController</code>
              </emphasis>: abstract controller that allows snapping to be
              enabled and disabled. When enabled, the returned points when
              asking <code>getPosition()</code>, are snapped (depending on the
              configured snapping rules).</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </note>

        <para>In order to disable the active controller, set a "null" value as
        controller:</para>

        <para><programlisting>mapWidget.setController(null);</programlisting></para>
      </section>

      <section id="activeAndFallback">
        <title>Active and fallback controllers</title>

        <para>Only one <code>GraphicsController</code> can be active at any
        one time on a map. This is done deliberately in order for controllers
        not to interfere with each other. By default the MapWidget uses a
        "fallback controller" that is activated when no explicit controller is
        set (a navigation controller by default). So when no explicit
        controller is set, or <code>mapWidget.setController(null)</code> is
        used, the map will turn to it's fallback controller.</para>

        <para>It is possible to replace this fallback controller by another
        than the default, by calling:</para>

        <programlisting>mapWidget.setFallbackController(&lt;the new controller&gt;);</programlisting>

        <para>In order to completely disable the use of a fallback controller,
        set "null" as the new fallback controller.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Addons on the map</title>

      <para>A way to let a user set controllers on the map is by providing
      addons for him/her on the map. Default addons are provided to pan and
      zoom in and out:</para>

      <para>Code-wise an addon is basically an (SmartGWT) widget composed out
      of background image, a foreground image (or icon) and a
      <code>GraphicsController.</code><figure>
          <title>Default map addons</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/defaultAddons.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>

      <para>Beside these default addons you can create your own addons by
      combining a background image, with an icon and a
      <code>GraphicsController</code> or a <code>ToolbarAction</code>.</para>

      <para>Before you can add your own addons however, your first need to
      disable the creation of the default addons by setting the property
      "panButtonsEnabled" of your <code>ClientMapInfo</code> bean to
      false.</para>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;bean name="mapNoNav" class="org.geomajas.configuration.client.ClientMapInfo"&gt; 
  &lt;property name="panButtonsEnabled" value="false" /&gt; 
&lt;/bean&gt;</programlisting><note>
          <para>The name of the <code>ClientMapInfo</code> bean is the id used
          in the constructor of the <code>MapWidget</code>.</para>
        </note></para>

      <para>Now you can create an addon by constructing a
      <code>SingleMapAddon</code>. Depending on your desires you can construct
      a <code>SingleMapAddon</code> in different ways:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>With just a icon or with a background image as well.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>With a <code>GraphicsController</code> or a
          <code>ToolbarAction.</code></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>With a explicit size or automatically based on the size of the
          given image(s).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The creation of a zoom-in <code>SingleMapAddon</code> can be
      achieved like this:</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/SingleMapAddon.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <para>A more complex zoom slider is created like this:</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/ZoomSliderMapAddon.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <programlisting>/*
 * Slider handler icon
 */
Image sliderUnit = ImageUtil.createRectangleImage(ZoomSlider.SLIDER_UNIT + "icon", 
Geomajas.getIsomorphicDir() + EXAMPLE_IMAGE_FOLDER + "sliderUnit.png", 0, 0, SLIDER_UNIT_WIDTH, SLIDER_UNIT_HEIGHT);
/*
 * Part of the background on which the zoomslider handler can move.
 * One zoom level is represented by one image.
 */
Image backgroundPart = ImageUtil.createRectangleImage(ZoomSlider.SLIDER + "Bg", 
Geomajas.getIsomorphicDir() + EXAMPLE_IMAGE_FOLDER + "sliderbg.png", 0, 0, SLIDER_WIDTH, SLIDER_PART_HEIGHT);
/*
 * Zoom in; the top of ZoomSlider
 */
Image in = ImageUtil.createSquareImage(ZOOM_IN + ICON,
Geomajas.getIsomorphicDir() + "geomajas/mapaddon/zoomPlus.png",
0, 0, SLIDER_WIDTH);
Image sliderTop = ImageUtil.createSquareImage(
ZoomSlider.SLIDER + "Top", Geomajas.getIsomorphicDir()
+ EXAMPLE_IMAGE_FOLDER + "sliderbgtop.png", 0, 0,
SLIDER_WIDTH);
SingleMapAddon zoomIn = new SingleMapAddon(ZOOM_IN, in, sliderTop,
mapWidget, new ZoomInAndOutController(mapWidget, 1.01));

/*
 * Zoom out; the bottom of ZoomSlider
 */
Image out = ImageUtil.createRectangleImage(ZOOM_OUT + ICON,
Geomajas.getIsomorphicDir() + "geomajas/mapaddon/zoomMinus.png", 
0, 0, SLIDER_WIDTH, SLIDER_WIDTH);
Image sliderBottom = ImageUtil.createRectangleImage(ZoomSlider.SLIDER
+ "Bottom", Geomajas.getIsomorphicDir() + EXAMPLE_IMAGE_FOLDER
+ "sliderbgbottom.png", 0, 0, SLIDER_WIDTH, SLIDER_WIDTH);
SingleMapAddon zoomOut = new SingleMapAddon(ZOOM_OUT, out,
sliderBottom, mapWidget, new ZoomInAndOutController(mapWidget,
0.99));

/*
 * Zoom slider itself
 */
ZoomSlider slider = new ZoomSlider(ZoomSlider.SLIDER, mapWidget);
slider.setZoomIn(zoomIn);
slider.setBackgroundPart(backgroundPart);
slider.setSliderUnit(sliderUnit);
slider.setZoomOut(zoomOut);
slider.setHorizontalMargin(HORIZONTAL_MIDDLE - SLIDER_WIDTH / 2);
slider.setVerticalMargin(pan.getVerticalMargin() + PAN_DIA + 2 * MARGIN);
mapWidget.registerMapAddon(slider);
/* And finally add the slider as a MapViewChangedHandler to let it's handle be adjusted, 
 * in case the zoomlevel is changed outside the slider.
 */
mapWidget.getMapModel().getMapView().addMapViewChangedHandler(slider);</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>For the full snippet in the Geomajas showcase, open the
        <abbrev>Map and rendering</abbrev> section, click the <abbrev>Zoom
        slider</abbrev> example and view the attached sources.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Listeners on the map</title>

      <para>As an alternative to the interactive controllers on a map, there
      are passive <code>Listeners</code> as well. These listener have an
      interface very much like the <code>GraphicsController</code> interface,
      but they never receive the real mouse events. As such they are meant to
      be passive observers, which receive notifications of mouse events. As
      opposed to the <code>GraphicsControllers</code>, these listeners are
      never allowed to interfere.</para>

      <para>As a result, multiple listeners can be registered on the map,
      while only one <code>GraphicsController</code> can be active at any
      given time. Instead of the real mouse events, listeners receive
      placeholder events of the type <code>ListenerEvent</code>. These
      <code>ListenerEvent</code> objects resemble the GWT mouse events a bit,
      and contain most of the information of the real mouse events.</para>

      <para>In order to add a listener to the map, or remove a listener from
      the map, your code should be something like this:</para>

      <programlisting>// Define a new Listener, starting from the AbstractListener:
Listener myListener = new AbstractListener() {
    public void onMouseMove(ListenerEvent event) {
        // Do something...
    }
};

// Add the Listener to the map:
mapWidget.addListener(myListener);

// Remove the Listener from the map:
mapWidget.removeListener(myListener);</programlisting>

      <para><note>
          <para>When creating a new Listener, often it is easiest to start
          from the <code>AbstractListener</code> class, which has all empty
          methods for catching the mouse events. In this case you override the
          methods for the events you are interested in.</para>
        </note></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Changing the cursor on the map</title>

      <para>The MapWidget in the GWT face provides the possibility to apply
      different cursors when hovering the map. In previous versions this was
      done through the <code>setCursor</code> method, which only supported
      default cursors. Since version 1.10 of the GWT face however, the
      <code>MapWidget</code> also provides the <code>setCursorString</code>
      method, which support custom images to be used as cursors on top of the
      default cursors.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="i18n">
    <title>Internationalization in Geomajas</title>

    <para>For internationalization, Geomajas uses the default GWT i18n
    implementation. For Geomajas specifically, the i18n is used in several
    places, each having it's own list of messages. Basically all i18n message
    definitions are located in the package
    <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.i18n</code>, as are the properties files
    containing the translations.</para>

    <para>Several separate definitions have been created:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>MenuMessages</emphasis>: the <code>MenuMessages</code>
        defines parameterized string values that are used in the titles of
        <code>MenuAction</code> classes. Examples are the editing context
        menus.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>ToolbarConstants</emphasis>: this defines strings that
        are used as tool tips when hovering over the buttons in the tool bar.
        This list of values is used by the <code>ToolbarAction</code> and
        <code>ToolbarSelectAction</code> classes. Note that for tool tips the
        "&amp;nbsp;" character is used instead of the default space.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>AttributeMessages</emphasis>: .....</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>GlobalMessages</emphasis>: .....</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>LayerTreeMessages</emphasis>: .....</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>SearchMessages</emphasis>: .....</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To avoid multiple instantiations of the constants and messages
    classes and have a central access point for all internationalization
    concerns, the <code>I18nProvider</code> class has been created. This class
    has static methods for accessing the constants and messages classes. Usage
    is as follows:</para>

    <programlisting>String dist = I18nProvider.getMenu().getMeasureDistanceString(totalDistance, radius); 
setContents( "&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;" + I18nProvider.getMenu().distance() + "&lt;/b&gt;:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div style='margin-top:5px;'&gt;" + dist + "&lt;/div&gt;"); </programlisting>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Styling and skinning</title>

    <para>The GWT face uses SmartGWT for the widgets, styling and skinning.
    The skin for the application is defined in your gwt.xml file. This can for
    example be done using something like:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;inherits name="com.smartclient.theme.simplicity.Simplicity" /&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>Extra tuning can be done in CSS.</para>

    <para>In some cases this is not sufficient. SmartGWT handles the flowing
    of widgets itself based on CSS and size and position information which is
    included in code. To alleviate this, there is a special class names
    WidgetLayout which contains many of the fixed values which are used for
    the sizing and styling used in the widgets. The fields in the class can be
    set on the onLoad() method in your GWT entry point class to influence the
    style of the widgets.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="junit">
    <title>Unit testing GWT widgets</title>

    <para>A GWT unit test should inherit from the <code>GWTTestcase</code>
    base class and should be named <code>GwtTestXxx.java</code>. GWT unit
    tests are run inside a development mode environment and can refer to most
    of the GWT API. To run a GWT test case, run the Maven command
    <command>gwt:test </command>or execute the integration test phase.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating (custom) feature forms</title>

    <remark>This functionality has been added to the GWT client API in version
    1.9.0.</remark>

    <para>When working with vector layers, one often has a need for editing
    not only the vector component of the features, but also the
    alpha-numerical attributes. To this end, special factories have been
    created that can be passed to the editing widgets (FeatureAttirbuteEditor
    and FeatureAttributeWindow) to create such forms.</para>

    <para>All interfaces and classes in this section can be found in the
    following package:
    <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.widget.attribute</code></para>

    <para>Central in all this, is the <code>FeatureForm</code> and the
    <code>FeatureFormFactory</code>. The <code>FeatureFormFactory</code> is an
    interface that defines a single method for the creation of a
    <code>FeatureForm</code> instance.</para>

    <example>
      <title>FeatureFormFactory interface</title>

      <para><programlisting>public interface FeatureFormFactory {

   /**
    * Creates a form using the specified attribute information.
    *
    * @param infos
    *           List of attribute definitions. Normally taken from a {@link VectorLayer}.
    * @return An attribute form that allows for editing of it's values.
    */
    FeatureForm createFeatureForm(VectorLayer layer);
}</programlisting></para>
    </example>

    <para>The default implementation of this factory has been implemented
    <code>as DefaultFeatureFormFactory</code>. This factory returns a default
    implementation for the feature form for each layer:
    <code>DefaultFeatureForm</code>. When the default layout of a feature form
    is sufficient use the <code>DefaultFeatureFormFactory</code> as is,
    otherwise feel free to implement your own factory that returns custom
    instances of a <code>FeatureForm</code>.</para>

    <para>The <code>FeatureForm</code> is a form definition that has been
    tuned towards the Geomajas GWT feature definition, and is used in the
    central editing widgets (<code>FeatureAttributeEditor</code> and
    <code>FeatureAttributeWindow</code>). Note that those editing widgets have
    constructors to accept a <code>FeatureFormFactory</code>, so you have to
    pass them a custom factory that returns your custom form.</para>

    <para>Of course implementing your own <code>FeatureForm</code> might be a
    bit overwhelming and fortunately is usually not necessary as you can
    easily extend the <code>DefaultFeatureForm</code> to suit your needs. The
    <code>DefaultFeatureForm</code> has several hooks to allow you to
    influence its layout:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>The <code>createField(AttributeInfo)</code> and/or
        <code>createItem(AttributeInfo)</code> methods can be overridden to
        customize form items or create your own.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <code>isIncluded(AttributeInfo)</code> method can be
        overridden to omit certain attributes.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>The <code>prepareForm(FormItemList, DataSource)</code> method
        can be overridden to set the layout properties of the form and add
        additional items such as spacers or headers.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Adding new form item types can also be done in a more global way.
    Therefore, an extra utility class has been added to create the individual
    form items that represent the feature's attributes. This utility class is
    the <code>AttributeFormFieldRegistry</code>. This registry keeps a
    pre-defined set of form item definitions and data source fields (both are
    necessary to successfully create forms in SmartGWT) that map onto
    attribute types. For example, it will map a DateItem and
    DataSourceDateField onto all attributes of type "DATE". This registry can
    now be used to create the individual items within the form, or to register
    custom form items types to use in the forms.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Internally, the
      <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.widget.attribute.DefaultFeatureForm</code>
      makes use of the AttributeFormFieldRegistry. This means that if you
      register custom form items for certain attribute types, these custom
      items will also appear in the default feature forms, without you having
      to implement a custom FeatureForm.</para>
    </note>

    <para>In the following sections, the details of registering custom form
    items and creating custom forms will be explained.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Using custom form items within a FeatureForm</title>

      <para>In order to use custom form items within a FeatureForm, there are
      2 ways: override one the default for a certain attribute type, or define
      a completely new type.</para>

      <para>In any case, you will need to register a custom type with the
      AttributeFormFieldRegistry. Let us start with a coding example:</para>

      <programlisting>// We define the custom type "myType" in the AttributeFormItemFactory:
        AttributeFormFieldRegistry.registerCustomFormItem("myType", new DataSourceFieldFactory() {

            public DataSourceField create() {
                return new DataSourceIntegerField();
            }
        }, new FormItemFactory() {

            public FormItem create() {
                return new SliderItem();
            }
        }, null);

</programlisting>

      <para>This short piece of code will register a "SliderItem" for all
      attributes of the type "myType". Let us first go over the code in more
      detail. In order to register a new type, 4 arguments are
      required:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The key associated with the given <code>FormItemFactory</code>
          and <code>DataSourceFieldFactory</code>. This key is either the name
          of an attribute type (i.e. <code>PrimitiveType.DATE.name()</code>)
          to overwrite the default definitions, or a completely new type which
          can be configured in the attribute definitions with the
          <code>formInputType</code> field (see further in this section). This
          key is a unique identifier. In the example above: "myType".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <code>DataSourceFieldFactory</code> definition. This factory
          will create a SmartGWT <code>DataSourceField</code> that represents
          the underlying data-source in the form.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A <code>FormItemFactory</code> definition. This factory will
          create a SmartGWT FormItem that represents the actual widget by
          which the attribute is presented in the form. In the case above, the
          attribute will be represented by a <code>SliderItem</code>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>A list of validators that can be attached to the underlying
          <code>DataSourceField</code>. Any time the user changes values
          within a FeatureForm, the associated validators will be executed. In
          the example above no extra validators are attached to the
          <code>DataSourceIntegerField (value null)</code>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>So the parameter explanation already told us how to overwrite the
      default attribute types: by registering a new type for an attribute type
      (i.e. <code>PrimitiveType.DATE.name()</code>). The other option, to
      register completely new types, is done by using a new key
      (i.e."myType"). The only thing left to do than is to associate
      attributes with this key. This can be done within the vector layer XML
      configuration, where a field by the name of "<code>formInputType</code>"
      can be added to an attribute configuration. For more information on
      attribute configuration, visit the configuration part in the <ulink
      url="http://files.geomajas.org/maven/trunk/geomajas/docbook-devuserguide/html/master.html#conf-vectorInfo">Geomajas
      developer guide</ulink>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using custom form items for association attributes</title>

      <para>Association attributes (one-to-many and many-to-one) require a
      specific treatment because they are too complex to be mapped to a
      single-valued form item. For these attributes, special interfaces have
      been constructed that provide full control over the way association
      value data travels between the feature and it's form
      representation:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The <code>ManyToOneItem</code> interface defines the contract
          for a custom form item that represents a many-to-one
          assocation</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>he <code>OneToManyItem</code> interface defines the contract
          for a custom form item that represents a one-to-many
          assocation</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Both interfaces contain the following methods:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code><code>getItem</code>()</code>: this methods returns the
          actual form item to be used in the form. This can either be an item
          that holds the actual value or a button or link that opens a more
          complex editor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>fromItem(), toItem()</code> : these methods govern the
          actual transfer of data between the form and the association value.
          This may include transfer from and to a more complex editor.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>init(AssociationAttributeInfo attributeInfo,
          AttributeProvider attributeProvider)</code>: this method provides a
          way to initialize the custom form item and/or editor. It passes
          information on the nested attributes of the association value and an
          attribute provider interface. The provider interface allows to query
          a list of possible attribute values in case the user has to select
          the value from a predefined list.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><code>clearValue() </code>: this method allows custom
          clearance of the form item and editor.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The default implementation of <code>ManyToOneItem</code> is a
      simple combobox.</para>

      <para>The default implementation of <code>OneToManyItem</code> is a
      "<code>More...</code>" link that pops up a master-detail editor
      configuration for editing a list of association values.</para>

      <para>These are in line with our default interpretation of a many-to-one
      attribute as being an association by reference to an externally managed
      list and a one-to-many item as being a parent-child relationship. Custom
      behavior can of course be implemented by registering a different
      implementation of the interfaces.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Creating a custom FeatureForm</title>

      <para>The next step is to create a custom <code>FeatureForm</code>. Let
      us again start with a short code example:<programlisting>public class AttributeCustomForm extends DefaultFeatureForm {

 public AttributeCustomForm(VectorLayer vectorLayer) {
  super(vectorLayer);
 }

 @Override
 protected FormItem createItem(AttributeInfo info) {
  FormItem formItem = super.createItem(info); // call super to create the default item
  formItem.setWidth("*");
  if ("dateAttr".equals(info.getName())) {
   // The date attribute will span all 4 columns:
   formItem.setColSpan(4);
  }
  return formItem;
 }

 @Override
 protected void prepareForm(FormItemList formItems, DataSource source) {
  // Quickly insert a row spacer before the 'stringAttr' item (which is the text area).
  formItems.insertBefore("stringAttr", new RowSpacerItem()); // inserting an item via the FormItemList
  getWidget().setNumCols(4);
  getWidget().setWidth(450);
  getWidget().setColWidths(100, 180, 20, 150);
  getWidget().setGroupTitle("Custom Attribute Form");
  getWidget().setIsGroup(true);
 }
}
</programlisting></para>

      <para>The <code>createItem(AttributeInfo info)</code> method is
      overridden to set the item width and make the date attribute span 4
      columns. The <code>prepareForm(FormItemList formItems, DataSource
      source)</code> method is overridden to insert an extra spacer item
      before the string attribute and set the general column layout. The form
      that results from this will not differ all too much from the default
      implementation, but it should get you on your way.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
