<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-gwt-widgets">
  <title>GWT widgets</title>

  <para>This second chapter of the GWT face describes all the widgets that
  Geomajas has added on top of the SmartGWT widget list. Each widget will be
  handled in detail so that developers might get a better understanding of
  what they are here for, and how to use them. Know that many of these widgets
  are closely connected, either through configuration or coding.</para>

  <section id="GraphicsWidget">
    <title>GraphicsWidget</title>

    <para>The <code>GraphicsWidget</code> is the basic widget that allows
    drawing onto a <code>GraphicsContext</code>, and catches mouse events at
    the same time. It implements the <code>MapContext</code> interface and
    provides it's own <code>MenuContext</code> implementation. As for the
    <code>VectorContext</code>, it delegates to a browser specific
    implementation (<code>VmlGraphicsContext</code> or
    <code>SvgGraphicsContext</code>). It is also responsible for handling
    <code>GraphicsController</code>s (only one global controller at a time!).
    The reason to place the controller handling here, is because we needed a
    default GWT widget to handle the events, not a SmartGWT widget. The
    SmartGWT events do not contain the actual DOM elements for MouseEvents,
    while the default GWT events do - for some functionality it is absolutely
    vital that it is well-known which DOM node was the target of an
    event.</para>

    <para>Using the MenuContext, this widget always has the coordinates of the
    latest right mouse click. Usually the right mouse button is used for
    drawing context menus. But sometimes it is necessary to have the DOM
    element onto which the context menu was clicked, to influence this menu.
    That is why this widget always stores this latest event (or at least it's
    DOM element id, and screen location).</para>

    <para>This widget is the bridge between the internal Svg or Vml rendering
    in GWT and the SmartGWT widget library. It is used internally in the
    MapWidget, but is not meant to be used directly by developers.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="MapWidget">
    <title>MapWidget</title>

    <para>The main map for any Geomajas application using the GWT face. This
    widget controls the <code>MapModel</code>, the <code>MapView</code>
    objects, has an internal <code>GraphicsWidget</code> for the actual
    rendering, and much more. Being the most central of all widget, the
    MapWidget has quite a few responsibilities and options.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Map - initialization</emphasis></para>

    <para>A first responsibility of the map is the correct initialization of
    it's model and all layers from the configuration. When the MapWidget is
    added to the HTML (onDraw), it will automatically fetch the configuration
    from the server, and than initialize itself (more precisely, build the
    <code>MapModel</code>). When this is done, the <code>MapModel</code> will
    fire a <code>MapModelEvent</code>. Many other widgets wait for this moment
    to initialize themselves, as they often require the
    <code>MapModel</code>'s contents.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">View - rendering</emphasis></para>

    <para>A second responsibility lies in the ability to render shapes. The
    <code>render()</code> method uses a <code>PainterVisitor</code> to
    recursively go through <code>Paintable</code> objects and look for the
    correct <code>Painter</code>. All <code>Painter</code> definitions must be
    registered in the <code>MapWidget</code>, by means of the
    <code>registerPainter()</code> and <code>unregisterPainter()</code>
    methods. Also the full list of <code>WorldPaintables</code> is stored
    within the <code>MapWidget</code>. For more information regarding the
    rendering, using the render method, visit the <link
    linkend="graphics"><corpauthor>rendering
    manual</corpauthor></link>.</para>

    <para>As an addition of the <code>Paintable</code> objects in
    screen-space, the definition of a <code>MapAddon</code> has been created
    as well. <code>MapAddons</code> are self regulating pieces of software
    that are visible at a certain location on the map (in screen space!), and
    optionally have attached behaviour. Examples are the Navigation buttons
    and the scale bar.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Controller</emphasis></para>

    <para>To add interactivity to a map, you can add two types of controllers:
    the <code>GraphicsController</code> and the GWT
    <code>MouseWheelHandler</code>. For both it is possible to apply a single
    instance using the <code>setController()</code> and
    <code>setMouseWheelController()</code> methods.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="bold">Options</emphasis></para>

    <para>On top of the previous list of responsibilities, the map also has a
    few options that allow certain functionality to be present or not. The
    following options are standard:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>navigationAddonEnabled</emphasis>: this option can be
        configured from within the configuration, and determines whether or
        not the navigation <code>MapAddon</code> is visible. This
        <code><code>MapAddon</code></code> is placed in the upper left corner
        of the map and allows the user to pan, zoom in and out, and zoom to
        maximum extent.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>scaleBarEnabled</emphasis>: this option can be
        configured from within the configuration, and determines whether or
        not the scale bar is visible. This shows you the scale of the map by
        means of a bar of certain length, expressed in the preferred unit type
        (metric versus English).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>zoomOnScrollEnabled</emphasis>: this option determines
        whether or not the <code>ZoomOnScrollController</code> is active by
        default. This allows zooming in and out on the map using the mouse
        wheel.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <figure>
      <title>MapWidget example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_mapwidget.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="OverviewMap">
    <title>OverviewMap</title>

    <para>The overview map is an extension of the <code>MapWidget</code>,
    which keeps the overview of a target <code><code>MapWidget</code></code>.
    It keeps track of the target map's view, and reacts whenever that target
    map changes it's view. The <classname>OverViewMap</classname> implements
    the <code>MapViewChangedHandler</code> to track the changes of it's target
    map. As it is an extension of a normal <code>MapWidget</code>, it has all
    the functionality of a normal map. So you can configure layers for an
    overview map, just as you would for a normal map.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>OverviewMap example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_overviewmap.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>What can be tricky is to properly configure the bounds of the
    overview map. In the image above, this is slightly bigger than the world
    (which in this case is probably not what you want). The bounds for the
    overview map normally uses the initial bounds as defined on the map.
    However, when you set the useTargetMapMaxExtent parameter to true when
    creating the overview map, following locations are checked, using the
    first which was configured:</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>targetMap.maxBounds</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>union of layer extents</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para>The bounds are automatically extended by a percentage. The default
    is 5%, but this can be configured when creating the overview map.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="Toolbar">
    <title>Toolbar</title>

    <para>The Geomajas tool bar is an extension of the SmartGWT
    <code>ToolStrip</code> widget, and allows for many different widgets to be
    added to it. A tool bar must be initialized with an instance of the
    <code>MapWidget</code> it is related to. When the <code>MapWidget</code>
    has successfully initialized itself, it's <code>MapModel</code> will fire
    the <code>MapModelEvent</code> saying so. The tool bar reacts on this
    event by searching in the map configuration for the correct list of tool
    bar buttons. The map configuration can contain tool ids to indicate the
    tools which need to be added, together with optional parameters. Using the
    <code>ToolbarRegistry</code>, which contains the mappings between these
    ids and the relevant <code>ToolbarAction</code> or
    <code>ToolbarModalAction</code> classes, the tool bar will initialize
    itself (for more info; see <link linkend="interaction">User
    Interaction</link>).</para>

    <para>Existing tools which can be defined include:</para>

    <para><itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>EditMode</emphasis>: a ToolbarModalAction for
          editing on the map. Allows the user to create new objects in the
          selected layer, and allows updating and deleting of selected
          objects.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>MeasureDistanceMode</emphasis>: a ToolbarModalAction
          which allows the user to measure distances on the map.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>SelectionMode</emphasis>: allow selecting features
          either by clicking on them, or by dragging a rectangle, thus
          selecting the features which are inside the rectangle. You need an
          active (vector) layer for the selection to work. The right click
          menu allows clearing the selected features and toggling selection at
          the current position. Press shift or control while selecting to add
          the selection to the previously selected features. Possible
          parameters:</para>

          <para><itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>clickTimeout</emphasis>: when the button it
                released in less than the number of milliseconds specified
                here, then the selection is treated as a click. When it takes
                longer, it is treated as dragging. Default is "500"
                (ms).</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>coverageRatio</emphasis>: ratio of the feature
                which needs to be inside the selected area for the feature to
                be selected. When this is "1.0" then the entire feature needs
                to be inside the selection rectangle. Default is "0.7".</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>priorityToSelectedLayer</emphasis>: when this
                is "true" selection will first check the selected layer, and
                use default behaviour only if nothing is found in that layer.
                Default behaviour is to try all visible layers, from front to
                back.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>pixelTolerance</emphasis>: number of pixels of
                tolerance allowed when trying to select features. The default
                pixel tolerance is 5.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ZoomIn</emphasis>: zoom in to the map at the
          location clicked (will be centered), using the zoom factor which is
          configured.</para>

          <para><itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>delta</emphasis>: zoom in factor, should be
                &gt;1 to effectively zoom in.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ZoomOut</emphasis>: zoom out of the map at the
          location clicked (will be centered), using the zoom factor which is
          configured.</para>

          <para><itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis>delta</emphasis>: zoom in factor, should be in
                the ]0,1[ range to effectively zoom out</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>PanMode</emphasis>: this action allows you to pan
          the screen by dragging. When keeping either the shift or control key
          down, it is also possible to indicate an area to zoom into (like
          <emphasis>ZoomToRectangleMode</emphasis>).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ZoomToRectangleMode</emphasis>: you can indicate a
          rectangle (by dragging) and it will zoom to make the selected area
          as big as possible while still entirely inside the map
          widget.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ZoomToSelection</emphasis>: first select some items
          on the map. After clicking on the the zoomToSelection button the map
          will be zoomed so that all selected items will fit nicely on the
          screen.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>panToSelection</emphasis>: first select some items
          on the map. After clicking on the panToSelection button the map will
          be panned in such a way that the center of the selected items is in
          the center of the screen.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ZoomPrevious</emphasis>: go back to the previous
          zoom level (and location).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ZoomNext</emphasis>: go forward again, cancelling a
          click on <emphasis>ZoomPrevious</emphasis>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>ScaleSelect</emphasis>: scale select drop-down
          box.</para>

          <para><itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>precision: precision of the scale. For example using
                1000 as precision ensure the value "1:12,345" is displayed as
                "1:12,000".</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>significantDigits: maximum number of significant digits
                to display in the scale. For example using 3 as value ensures
                that "1:1,234,567" is displayed as "1:1,230,000".</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <figure>
      <title>Tool bar example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_toolbar.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="LayerTree">
    <title>LayerTree</title>

    <para>This widget represents a view on the map model which is focused on
    layers. You see the map layers in a tree, just as they are configured.
    Accompanied with this view, there are buttons that define certain actions
    on these layers. Originally there are no buttons in this widget, so they
    have to be added manually or through configuration. These buttons can
    either be single actions or selectable buttons (similar to the
    <code>Toolbar</code> widget - see <link linkend="interaction">User
    Interaction</link>).</para>

    <para>Just like the tool bar, the <code>LayerTree</code> waits for the
    <code>MapModel</code> to be initialized, and also reacts to the
    <code>MapModelEvent</code>. The layer tree configuration is contained in
    the map configuration. When the <code>MapModelEvent</code> is fired, the
    <code>LayerTree</code> will read configuration to know the layer tree
    structure, which buttons to include,...</para>

    <para>Below you see a screen shot of a simple <code>LayerTree</code> where
    no layer has been selected (and thus all the buttons are disabled):</para>

    <figure>
      <title>LayerTree example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_layertree1.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Once a layer is selected, the <code>LayerTree</code> will ask all
    buttons whether they should be enabled for that layer. For example, the
    <code>org.geomajas.gwt.client.action.layertree.LabelAction</code>, which
    toggles a layer's labels, is only applicable on vector layers, so if the
    selected layer is a raster layer, that button will remain disabled. The
    same <code>LayerTree</code> with a selected layer looks like this:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>LayerTree with selected layer</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_layertree2.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The <code>LayerTree</code> has few public methods, but it does quite
    a lot behind the screen. The tree is a SmartGWT <code>TreeGrid</code>,
    where the <code>LayerTree</code> adds handlers to the nodes and leaves
    (using <code>LeafClickHandler</code> and <code>FolderClickHandler</code>),
    which trigger layer selection in the <code>MapModel</code>. The
    <code>LayerTree</code> also listens to layer selection events, to adjust
    it's own appearance. For example, when a layer is selected, the proper
    node has to be selected and all the buttons updated.</para>

    <para>The <code>LayerTreeAction</code> and
    <code>LayerTreeModalAction</code> are also specifically designed to cope
    with the different stages that they should be able to display. The
    <code>LayerTreeModalAction</code> can be disabled, enabled and selected or
    enabled and deselected. For each it is imperative that clear markings are
    given. This means that different icons are usually used for the different
    stages. These different icons should be given to the actions at
    construction time.</para>

    <para>Currently the following actions are defined:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>org.geomajas.gwt.client.action.layertree.VisibleAction</emphasis>:
        a <code>LayerTreeModalAction</code> that switches the visible flag on
        the selected layer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>org.geomajas.gwt.client.action.layertree.LabelAction</emphasis>:
        a <code>LayerTreeModalAction</code> that switches the display of
        labels for the selected layer.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>org.geomajas.gwt.client.action.layertree.LayerRefreshAction</emphasis>:
        a <code>LayerTreeAction</code> that refreshes the selected layer on
        click.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="Legend">
    <title>Legend</title>

    <para>The <code>Legend</code> is a graphical widget that shows all styles
    for the currently visible vector layers. In that sense it is another view
    on the map model that only shows the style definitions that are currently
    relevant. Just like the map widget, the legend is built on
    <code>GraphicsWidget</code>. It reads the available layers from the map
    model and draws a legend to match the style of these layers.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Legend</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gwtface_widget_legend.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="FeatureListGrid">
    <title>FeatureListGrid</title>

    <para>The <code>FeatureListGrid</code> is a table listing the attributes
    of features within a single vector layer. Each feature is represented by a
    row in the grid, with at the top a header that shows the attribute label,
    as configured in the configuration. As only vector layers can contain
    features, the grid will be empty for raster layers.</para>

    <para>The <code>FeatureListGrid</code> has a few options that determine
    it's behaviour and appearance:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>selectionEnabled</emphasis>: enables or disables
        selection of features when selecting a row in the table. When this is
        enabled, the table will keep feature selection consistent with the map
        model. If the user selects a row, the feature will also be selected on
        the map.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>allAttributesDisplayed</emphasis>: show all attributes
        (true) or only the 'identifying' attributes (false)? Attributes can be
        configured as "identifying" in the configuration. This difference
        allows for a select list of attributes to be visible in the grid,
        keeping overview. The user can always ask more details by double
        clicking the line.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>editingEnabled</emphasis>: determines whether or not
        editing the attributes is allowed. When double clicking a row in the
        table, a <code>FeatureAttributeWindow</code> will appear, containing
        the feature of the selected row. This setting determines if that
        window allows editing or not.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><emphasis>idInTable</emphasis>: show the feature's id in the
        table. This is false by default, and should not really be
        necessary.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This table is an extension of the SmartGWT <code>ListGrid</code>
    widget. It automatically has grouping, filtering and sorting abilities
    (and much more...). The <code>FeatureListGrid</code> makes it possible to
    easily display features. You have to set the layer from which to display
    features. Then you can add features one by one. If no layer is set, then
    then "<code>addFeature</code>" method will not add any rows to the table.
    Setting the layer will automatically create the grid header, using the
    layer's attribute definitions.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>FeatureListGrid example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_featurelistgrid.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="FeatAttrWind">
    <title>FeatureAttributeWindow</title>

    <para>The <code>FeatureAttributeWindow</code> is a floating window to
    display and enable editing of a feature's attributes and persist these
    changes. This widget is a <code>FeatureAttributeEditor</code> with some
    extra buttons like "save". When setting a feature, it first makes a clone
    so you are not editing the feature directly and changes are only applied
    when the save is clicked. This widget also checks whether or not all
    fields are valid, and will not allow saving when at least one of the
    fields is not valid.</para>

    <para>The <code>FeatureAttributeWindow</code> has the following
    options:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>editingAllowed: is editing allowed? This must be set
        <emphasis>before</emphasis> the widget is actually drawn.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>editingEnabled: is editing currently enabled or not? This widget
        can toggle this value on the fly. When editing is enabled, it will
        display an editable attribute form with save, cancel and reset
        buttons. When editing is not enabled, these buttons will disappear,
        and a simple attribute form is shown that displays the attribute
        values, but does not allow editing. This effect only works when
        <emphasis>editingAllowed</emphasis> is true.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Below is a screen shot of a <code>FeatureAttributeWindow</code> with
    editing allowed but not enabled. Without the editing allowed, there would
    be now "edit" button. The button itself triggers setting editing
    enabled.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>FeatureAttributeWIndow, editing allowed but not enabled</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_featureattributewindow.png"
                     width="60%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="ActivityMon">
    <title>ActivityMonitor</title>

    <para>This widget monitors client-server communication traffic, and
    displays that activity to the end-user. It's purpose is inform the user
    that a server request is in progress. For example, when the user zooms in,
    it can sometimes take a few seconds before everything is redrawn. This
    widget displays that traffic by listening to the
    <code>GwtCommandDispatcher</code> events. On the screen shot below, you
    can see the difference between it being passive and active:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>ActivityMonitor example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_activitymonitor.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="ScaleSelect">
    <title>ScaleSelect</title>

    <para>Combo box for changing the scale on the map which can be added to a
    tool bar. It displays a list of possible scales to choose from, but also
    allows the user to type a specific scale. The scale select is constructed
    with a <code>MapView</code> as parameter. If this <code>MapView</code>
    contains pre-configured resolutions (zoom-steps - these can be set in the
    configuration), than the scale select will allow selection from these
    scales. If no resolutions are present, the scale select will automatically
    choose relevant scales to choose from.</para>

    <para>Using the <code>setScales()</code> method, one can always override
    the list of scales in the widget.</para>

    <para>The setPrecision() and setSignificantDigits() methods allow you to
    configure the rounding which is applied on the displayed scale
    values.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>ScaleSelect example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/gwtface_widget_scaleselect.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section id="FeatureSearch">
    <title>FeatureSearch</title>

    <para>Widget that supports searching for features on the attributes.
    Requires a value for <code>manualLayerSelection</code> at construction
    time. If true, a select box will be shown so the user can select what
    layer to search in. The possible list of layers consists of all the vector
    layers that are present in the map model. If false, this widget will
    search in the currently selected layer.</para>

    <para>When the "search" button is indicated, the search will be performed
    server-side. When the result returns, a <code>SearchEvent</code> is fired.
    This event holds a reference to the <code>VectorLayer</code> in which the
    search took place, and a list of all the features that were found. In
    order to do something with the results (such as displaying in a
    <code>FeatureListGrid</code>), add a <code>SearchHandler</code>. For the
    specific case of displaying the feature in a <code>FeatureListGrid</code>,
    there is a <code>DefaultSearchHandler</code> that already does
    this.</para>

    <para>Note that there is a limit to the number of features that are
    returned. By default this limit is set to 100. Modify
    <code>maximumResultSize</code> to change this. Note that a high limit can
    have a serious impact on performance and memory consumption!</para>

    <figure>
      <title>FeatureSearch example</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center"
                     fileref="images/gwtface_widget_featuresearch.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>
