<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2012 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The PureGWT face is an AJAX client for the Geomajas Server, based
  upon the Google Web Toolkit. The goal of this client is to be as light as
  possible, so it can easily run on mobile devices.</para>

  <para>Contrary to the GWT face, this face provides only one widget: the map.
  It does not come with a widget library either. It focuses entirely on
  providing a clean GIS API. In a sense this face is somewhat similar to the
  Google Maps API, except that it still relies on the Geomajas server.</para>

  <sect1>
    <title>Thin client</title>

    <para>Since the Geomajas Server is perfectly capable of safeguarding your
    domain model or executing complex tasks, this client can focus more on the
    map presentation than business logic. This already makes the PureGWT face
    a real thin client. Take also the use of the Google Web Toolkit (GWT) into
    account and this client becomes even thinner.</para>

    <para>The Google Web Toolkit is a Java to JavaScript compiler, that
    compiles only the code that you're actually using. So instead of having to
    download entire JavaScript libraries of which you're only using a small
    portion, a GWT application contains only code that is actually used.
    Secondly, GWT provides a lot of tools for further optimizing the way your
    applications are constructed. It provides automatic obfuscation, resource
    bundling (combining resources so that less requests are needed to loads
    them all), etc.</para>

    <para>As a result of all this optimization, the memory consumption within
    the browser is also kept at a minimum, while performance is kept at
    maximum.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Mobile vs desktop</title>

    <para>Although aimed towards mobile devices, the PureGWT face is
    perfectly suitable for both desktop and mobile environments. As mentioned
    above, the initial footprint is as small as possible (easily a factor 10
    smaller than other frameworks). On top of this, the PureGWT face is also
    designed to keep client-server bandwidth to a minimum, by providing
    caching mechanisms, lazy loading, etc.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
