<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This plugin provides client side WMS (Web Map Service) support. It
  defines services to communicate with backend WMS services and it also
  provides a client-side layer definition. The main difference with the
  Geomajas-Layer-WMS plugin is that the layers are defined client-only. That
  means that they are not part of the backed map composition. That in turn
  means .....</para>

  <section>
    <title>Client-side WMS versus server-side WMS</title>

    <para>As you may know, Geomajas also has the Geomajas-Layer-WMS plugin.
    That plugin defines a server-side WMS layer. The main difference is that
    the Geomajas-Layer-WMS plugin defines the WMS layers in the backend map
    composition, making it available to all users. This client-side WMS plugin
    on the other hand is able to define client WMS layers. These are available
    only on the client that adds them, making them more flexible.</para>

    <para>Note that if your WMS server is located on another domain, the
    browser will prohibit you from accessing it directly. In that case you
    will need to go through the server anyway, although a proxy servlet should
    suffice. If you need extra security measures, this proxy servlet would be
    the place to do it. The serverside WMS layer already has security measures
    built in.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Supported functionalities</title>

    <section>
      <title>WMS Requests</title>

      <para>This plugin provides a client WMS service definition that supports
      WMS requests:
      <code>org.geomajas.plugin.wmsclient.client.service.WmsService</code></para>

      <para><code>This WmsService provides support for the following WMS
      requests:</code></para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>GetCapabilities</emphasis>: Executes a WMS
          GetCapabilities and parses the result into Java objects. This
          capabilities object allows you to read the WMS contact information,
          the list of supports coordinate reference systems, the list of known
          layers, etc.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>GetMap</emphasis>: A GetMap request gets an image
          for a certain location. This request is used by the layer
          renderer.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>GetLegendGraphic</emphasis>: A GetLegendGraphic
          request gets an image for the legend of a certain layer. This legend
          displays styling information.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>GetFeatureInfo</emphasis>: The GetFeatureInfo
          request is used to request feature information for a specific
          location. Depending on the return type, this information can be
          parsed as a list of Feature objects.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Layer definitions</title>

      <para>This plugin provides not one, but two layer definitions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>WmsLayer</emphasis>: The basic WMS layer definition.
          This will display a WMS layer on the map, and also supports the
          GetLegendGraphic to display the legend.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>FeaturesSupportedWmsLayer</emphasis>: An extension
          of the basic WMS layer definition that also support the
          GetFeatureInfo request. Not all WMS layer will support this
          feature.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Map Controllers</title>

      <para>By default this plugin provides the following
      MapControllers:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>WmsGetFeatureInfoController</emphasis>: Controller
          that executes GetFeatureInfo requests on mouse clicks. This
          controller does not extend the NavigationController, and can best be
          used as a MapListener next to the default
          NavigationController.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>GIN</title>

      <para>This plugin extends the default Geomajas injection definitions, by
      providing it's own GIN module definition and GIN injector interface.
      Through this GIN injector, one can create new WMS Layers or acquire the
      WmsService singleton.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Versions</title>

    <para>This plugin has support for WMS version 1.1.1 and 1.3.0.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
