<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!--
  ~ This file is part of Geomajas, a component framework for building
  ~ rich Internet applications (RIA) with sophisticated capabilities for the
  ~ display, analysis and management of geographic information.
  ~ It is a building block that allows developers to add maps
  ~ and other geographic data capabilities to their web applications.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2010 Geosparc, http://www.geosparc.com, Belgium
  ~
  ~ This program is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify
  ~ it under the terms of the GNU Affero General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the
  ~ License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  ~ MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
  ~ GNU Affero General Public License for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Affero General Public License
  ~ along with this program.  If not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>.
  -->
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The GWT face allows you to use Java code for development of your AJAX
  based GIS web applications. It uses Google Web Toolkit and the SmartGWT
  widget library to have powerful widget which look nice.</para>

  <para>GWT is a toolkit from Google which is used amongst others for the
  development of Google AdWords and Google Wave. It compiles your Java code to
  JavaScript to allow the code to run on the client side, in the browser.
  While doing so, it takes care of many browser idiosyncrasies to alleviate
  the need to consider browser compatibility issues. GWT tries to make the
  user experience as comfortable as possible, to a large extent by focusing on
  responsiveness of the user interface. It combines all code and aggressively
  compresses that to reduce loading delays and allow caching. When the script
  file gets large, you still have the option to split it to reduce load time
  (the other parts are then loaded asynchronously. It also contains support
  for building internationalized applications, for combining resources
  etc.</para>

  <para>For the developer, there is the ability to run your applications in
  development mode. Though this is slower than production mode, it does remove
  the need for the full compilation before application startup (a big
  improvement as GWT produces different code per browser and language pair),
  and what's more, it allows debugging your application in Java!</para>
</chapter>
