<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the Apache
  ~ License, Version 2.0. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>The Geomajas graphics Project is a stand-alone project under the
  Geomajas banner.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <para>The Geomajas Graphics project will provide drawing capabilities
    (SVG, VML) in support of advanced client side redlining, annotation or
    mark-ups. Basic use cases are dragging resizing, labeling, styling and
    CRUD. The idea is to create a graphics library that does not necessarily
    depend on the Geomajas client, but draws directly into SVG or VML. By
    doing so we could create a general purpose graphics library that might be
    useful outside Geomajas or even the GIS world as well. The project is will
    therefore not depend on any a priori geographical constructs like
    coordinate spaces or transformations. In Geomajas speak, the project
    focusses on annotating objects in screen space, not in world space
    (although the latter will emerge from world referencing the screen
    objects, but this is considered a separate stage).</para>

    <para>The idea is to support different types of annotations and
    interaction mechanisms, some of which are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>graphical objects of varying nature, primarily based on what is
        available in SVG: points/markers, rectangles, ellipses, paths, lines,
        polygons, images, text</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>object attributes like color, font, line style, opacity</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>associations of text with objects, also known as labeling</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>specific objects like notes, callouts, popups</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>basic operations like adding, deleting, dragging, resizing,
        moving back/front</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>advanced operations like styling, coordinate-by-coordinate
        editing, uploading images, grouping</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The goal is to achieve the equivalent of typical drawing
    applications like PowerPoint or OpenOffice Draw, etc... but with a focus
    on annotating other objects (think geographical features or
    imagery).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Relationship with other Geomajas projects</title>

    <para>The project will of course smoothly integrate with the Geomajas
    Client and, in combination with the Geometry Editing plug-in, you should
    be able to reuse the intuïtive, yet powerful ways of changing the Path
    (add/remove intermediate points, etc.). The following picture illustrates
    the relationship of the Graphics project with other projects:</para>

    <para><figure>
        <title>Project interrelationship</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/projectview.png" width="75%" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>The project depends on the GWT Graphics project for rendering
    and the Geometry project for simple geometry concepts and geometrical
    calculations. The Geomajas Editing plugin will be extended with an extra
    module that hooks up the geometry editor to the graphical object
    controller framework (see architecture), making sure that the Graphics
    project itself stays light-weight and independent of the more complex
    editing mechanisms defined by the Editing plugin.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Requirements for the first iteration</title>

    <para>The initial version of the project will support the following object
    types:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Rectangle</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Ellipse (including circles)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Image</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Path</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The following operations will be available:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Initial object creation</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Dragging/resizing</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Labeling</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Deleting</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Undo/redo</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Moving objects back and front</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Object selection</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Object persistence: preferably standards, through SVG</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Basic concepts and architecture</title>

    <para>A <code>GraphicsObject</code> is an object that can be rendered in a
    <code>GraphicsObjectContainer</code>. The container supports
    addition/removal and update of objects and sends out events on the
    <code>EventBus</code> for each of these operations. The
    GraphicsObjectContainer wraps the "physical"
    <code>VectorObjectContainer</code> that implements the rendering of the
    objects in SVG or VML.</para>

    <para>A <code>GraphicsObject</code> supports different types of roles,
    depending on the context and the operation that the object is subjected
    to. The following roles can be distinguished: <code>Draggable</code>,
    <code>Resizable</code>, <code>Fillable</code>, <code>Strokable</code>,
    <code>Labeled</code> and so on. Possible <code>GraphicsObject</code>
    implementations are <code>GRectangle</code>, <code>GEllipse</code>,
    <code>GImage</code>, etc...Graphics objects usually do not directly
    implement these roles but use role-composition instead, making them
    dynamically extensible. Graphics objects can be rendered by supporting the
    <code>Renderable</code> role.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Graphical objects and roles</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/graphicsobject.png"
                     width="75%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>A <code>GraphicsObjectController</code> is responsible for
    interpreting user events and converting them into operations that will
    eventually be applied to the graphics objects by the
    <code>GraphicsService</code> (see further). The controller has access to
    the <code>VectorObjectContainer</code> to render helper objects like
    handlers (for resizing), drag lines (while creating a path) or drag masks
    (while dragging) and can register for whatever mouse events or key events
    it is interested in. Possible <code>GraphicsObjectController</code>
    implementations are <code>DragAndResizeController</code>,
    <code>DeleteController</code>, <code>EditGeometryController</code>,
    <code>PropertyEditController</code>, etc...Controllers act on one object
    only (controller-per-instance or a single controller for all instances
    with varying object scope) and can be activated and deactivated.</para>

    <para>Activation can be achieved by defining a special meta-controller
    that activates the controller(s) for a specific object. Initially a
    single-selection meta-controller that activates all controllers at once by
    clicking on the object should be sufficient. All controllers that act on a
    single object should be able to coexist. This implies that controllers do
    not register for all <code>VectorObjectContainer</code> events but instead
    delegate their work to specific helper objects like resize handlers, drag
    masks or special icons (e.g. to activate a specific editor).</para>

    <para>The <code>GraphicsService</code> is a manager class that manages the
    <code>GraphicsObjectContainer</code>, instantiates the
    <code>GraphicsObjectController</code> objects (and acts a registry for
    their factories) and executes <code>GraphicsOperations</code> on the
    <code>GraphicsObject</code> instances. A <code>GraphicsOperation</code> is
    undoable and redoable by keeping sufficient information to restore the
    object state to what it was before the operation.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Graphics service and controllers</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/graphicsservice.png" width="75%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</chapter>
