<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-javascript-configuration">
  <title>JavaScript Api for Editing</title>

  <para>The editing plug-in also provides a JavaScript API for client-side
  integration with other technologies. The API resembles the Java/GWT API as
  closely as possible (package names are different).</para>

  <section>
    <title>Maven configuration</title>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The GeometryEditService</title>

    <para>The JavaScript counterpart of the GeometryEditService is basically a
    wrapper around the GWT version. It therefore has the same methods, and
    works the same way.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using snapping</title>

    <para>The snapping options in JavaScript are not as rich as they are in
    GWT. No separate SnappingService is available. What can be done, is
    configuring snapping options in the XML configuration of the vector
    layers, and using that configuration directly. The JavaScript
    "GeometryEditor" has methods for activating those snapping rules during
    editing.</para>

    <para>On top of that, the GeometryEditor also has the ability to turn
    snapping on and off while inserting vertices or while dragging vertices.
    As with the GWT snapping you need at least one snapping rule for snapping
    to occur.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Merging geometries</title>

    <para>The JavaScript counterpart of the GeometryMergeService is basically
    a wrapper around the GWT version. It therefore has the same methods, and
    works the same way.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Splitting geometries</title>

    <para>The JavaScript counterpart of the GeometrySplitService is basically
    a wrapper around the GWT version. It therefore has the same methods, and
    works the same way.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
