<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2013 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-configuration">
  <title>Configuration</title>

  <para>The configuration of staticsecurity involves the following
  elements:</para>

  <para><itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>configure the use of staticsecurity as security service.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>configure the way to access the users.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>configure the policies to use.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

  <section id="dependencies">
    <title>Dependencies</title>

    <para>Make sure you include the correct version of the plugin in your
    project. This can be done either by including a reference to geomajas-dep
    or the following excerpt (with the correct version) in the
    dependencyManagement section of your project:</para>

    <informalexample>
		<programlisting> &lt;dependency&gt;
   &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.project&lt;/groupId&gt;
   &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-project-server&lt;/artifactId&gt;
   &lt;version&gt;<?eval ${project.version}?>&lt;/version&gt;
   &lt;type&gt;pom&lt;/type&gt;
   &lt;scope&gt;import&lt;/scope&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <para>If you are using geomajas-dep, this includes the latest version of
    the staticsecurity plugin (at the time of publishing of that version). If
    you want to overwrite the staticsecurity plugin version, make sure to
    include this excerpt <emphasis>before</emphasis> the geomajas-dep
    dependency.</para>

    <para>You can now include the actual dependency without explicit
		version:</para>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.plugin&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-plugin-staticsecurity&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <para>In case your users are stored in LDAP, you will need to include a
    dependency on the LDAP module:</para>

    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>&lt;dependency&gt;
    &lt;groupId&gt;org.geomajas.plugin&lt;/groupId&gt;
    &lt;artifactId&gt;geomajas-plugin-staticsecurity-ldap&lt;/artifactId&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</programlisting>
    </informalexample>
  </section>

  <section id="confUsers">
    <title>Configure users</title>

    <para>Users can be configured either statically or dynamically.</para>

    <section id="consUsersStatic">
      <title>Static configuration of users</title>

      <para>In the bean of type SecurityServiceInfo you can define the users
      which exist. This allows only password based authentication.</para>

      <para>The userId is also used as login. You can add a couple of extra
      fields to give information about the user.</para>

      <para>The password needs to be specified as a base64 encoded MD5 hash.
      The string to be hashed is a concatenation of</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>"Geomajas is a wonderful framework" (without quotes)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>user id</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>actual password</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>There is an online tool which can be used to calculate this has as
      <ulink
      url="http://progs.be/md5.html">http://progs.be/md5.html</ulink>.</para>

      <para>The authorizations property allow you to specify the policies,
      indicating what is allowed for the user.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/ConfigureUsers.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Static configuration of users (role-based)</title>

      <para>The static security has limited support for role-based user
      configuration. Particularly, the GetUsersCommand supports querying of
      users based on the roles they have. To make use of this functionality,
      static users should be configured by specifying a set of named roles and
      assigning these roles to the users. This is done by configuring the
      roles property (versus configuring the authorizations directly). A named
      role is a named list of authorizations.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/ConfigureUserRoles.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="confUsersDyn">
      <title>Dynamic configuration of users</title>

      <para>The user information can also be determined dynamically by
      explicitly configuring authentication services. The statically defined
      users (see previous section) are always automatically included after the
      configured authentication services.</para>

      <para>Below is a simple example from the tests which shows a
      configuration of an authentication service.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/CustomAuthenticationService.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="confUsersLdap">
      <title>Using LDAP to store user information</title>

      <para>Below is an example configuration for obtaining user information
      from an LDAP store.</para>

      <para>You have to configure the host and port for the LDAP server. The
      template to build the user DN<footnote>
          <para>distinguished named</para>
        </footnote> from the user id needs to be given. In the template the
      pair of braces ("{}") is replaced by the actual login. You can also
      define the attributes which are used to store the various pieces of user
      information. The given name and surname are concatenated (separated by a
      space) when both have a value.</para>

      <para>The roles property is used to define the authorizations for the
      roles which are configured in the LDAP store. The keys are the values of
      the roles attribute, often DN values. You can also define the
      defaultRole. This is the set of authorizations which is always assigned
      to all users who can authenticate using LDAP (the authorizations for the
      roles are added to that set).</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/LdapAuthentication.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>User directories</title>

      <para>Authentication services can provide support for querying their
      user base. This is done by implementing the
      <code>UserDirectoryService</code> interface. An authentication service
      that behaves as a user directory should implement the following
      method:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>List&lt;UserInfo&gt; getUsers(UserFilter
          userFilter);</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>This method accepts a user filter and returns a list of users that
      comply with the filter. An allow-all filter
      (<code>AllUserFilter</code>), logical filters
      (<code>AndUserFilter</code>, <code>OrUserFilter</code>) and a role
      filter (<code>RoleUserFilter</code>) are provided. Other filters can be
      added by subclassing <code>AbstractUserFilter</code> and implementing
      the actual filtering in the authentication service. </para>

      <para>For the static authentication service, the following method must
      be overridden:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>public boolean evaluate(UserFilter filter, UserInfo
          userInfo)</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For the LDAP authentication service, the following method provides
      a similar hook:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><code>public Filter convert(UserFilter filter)</code></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="confPolicies">
    <title>Configure policies</title>

    <para>The policies are configured by providing a list of authentications.
    Several ways exist, but they all start from the base layer
    policies.</para>

    <section id="policiesBase">
      <title>Base layer policies policies</title>

      <para>The base policies which always need to be provided include</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>which commands can be executed</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>which tools can be included in the UI</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>CRUD rights which are available for the layers</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For each of these policies, you can use regular expressions to
      indicate either what to include or what to exclude. By default you have
      no rights. You have to indicate what is included and can then refine
      that list by excluding some stuff from what was included.</para>

      <para>The base configuration to allow everything is displayed
      below:</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/BaseLayerPolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <para>You can explicitly configure which commands can be executed by
      that user.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/CommandPolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <para>You can also specify the tools which are allowed to be displayed
      in the UI.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/ToolPolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />

      <para>Importantly, you can configure the CRUD rights for each of the
      layers. You can specify for each layer, using include and exclude
      regular expressions, whether the user</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>can view the layer</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>add features in the layer</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>edit features for the layer</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>delete features from the layer</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <xi:include href="listing/LayerPolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="policiesAre">
      <title>Configure policies based on an area or geometry</title>

      <para>Using AreaAuthorizationInfo you can make your policies more
      granular by defining the are in which the CRUD operations are allowed.
      You first have to define the normal layer rights. You can then make this
      more specific by setting the geometry for the rights in the layers
      property, setting the area for each of the CRUD operations in for the
      specific layer. The actual geometry is specified using <ulink
      url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Well-known_text">WKT</ulink>.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/AreaPolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="policiesFilter">
      <title>Configure policies using a layer filter</title>

      <para>Using the LayerFilterAuthorizationInfo authorization bean you can
      add a ECQL filter to a layer to limit the features which can be
      read.</para>

      <para>This is done using the filters property which contains a map where
      the key is the (server) layers id and the value is the filter
      string.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/FilterPolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="policiesFeature">
      <title>Configure policies for individual features</title>

      <para>You can also be specific about which features in a layer are
      accessible by the user. This can be done using the
      FeatureAuthorizationInfo authorization bean.</para>

      <para>Using the layers property, you can determine which CRUD rights are
      allowed for which features. The property contains a map with the
      (server) layer id as key and a LayerFeatureAuthorizationInfo bean as
      value. This allows you to select the features using include and exclude
      rules on the feature id. As this only allows you to select on feature
      ids, consider this bean as an example for building more powerful feature
      selection policies.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/FeaturePolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>

    <section id="policiesAttr">
      <title>Configure policies for individual attributes</title>

      <para>The most specific access policies can be built using the
      AttributeAuthorizationInfo authorization bean. This allows you to
      specify which attributes can be used for specific features.</para>

      <para>Using the layers property, you can determine which CRUD rights are
      allowed for which features. The property contains a map with the
      (server) layer id as key and a LayerAttributeAuthorizationInfo bean as
      value. This allows you to select the attributes using include and
      exclude rules on the attribute name. You can add a "@featureId" suffix
      to the regular expression to limit the attribute to a features (using a
      regular expression on the feature id). As this only allows you to select
      on feature ids, consider this bean as an example for building more
      powerful attribute selection policies.</para>

      <xi:include href="listing/AttributePolicies.xml"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>
