<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ This is part of Geomajas, a GIS framework, http://www.geomajas.org/.
  ~
  ~ Copyright 2008-2014 Geosparc nv, http://www.geosparc.com/, Belgium.
  ~
  ~ The program is available in open source according to the GNU Affero
  ~ General Public License. All contributions in this program are covered
  ~ by the Geomajas Contributors License Agreement. For full licensing
  ~ details, see LICENSE.txt in the project root.
  -->

<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This plug-in represents a vector layer implementation based upon the
  popular Hibernate O/R mapping framework. It uses a special spatial extension
  of Hibernate, unsurprisingly called Hibernate Spatial. The Hibernate Spatial
  project has its project website at <ulink
  url="http://www.hibernatespatial.org/">http://www.hibernatespatial.org</ulink>.
  The spatial extensions or dialects (in Hibernate language), that Hibernate
  Spatial adds, allow the definition of spatial types and the execution of
  spatial queries in a database independent way.</para>

  <para>At this moment, the Hibernate layer plug-in supports the following
  databases:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Oracle SDO; It has been tested with Oracle 10i, but it should work
      equally well with Oracle 9i and Oracle 11g.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Postgresql/PostGIS: PostGIS 1.1.6 and higher.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Mircosoft SQL server 2008. Currently only the Geometry types are
      supported.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>MySQL: Works with MySQL 5.0 and higher. Note that MySQL does not
      completely implement the OGC Simple Feature Specification. Some
      functions that work for PostGIS or Oracle may fail to work for
      MySQL.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The real strength of this plug-in lies in the fact that it allows you
  to deal with geographic data in a standardized way. It abstracts away from
  the specific way your database supports geographic data, and provides a
  standardized, cross-database interface to geographic data storage and query
  functions.</para>
</chapter>
